<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Klētoi tetērēmēnoi, or, The Saints perseverance asserted in its positive grounds and vindicated from all material exceptions against it occasioned by a late immodest account of two conferences upon that point, between Tho. Danson and Mr. Jer. Ives, published by the said Mr. Ives, which account is also herein rectified, and its falshood detected to the just shame of the publisher / by Tho. Danson.</title>
            <author>Danson, Thomas, d. 1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24868</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08630093</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08630093</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36522)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1255:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Klētoi tetērēmēnoi, or, The Saints perseverance asserted in its positive grounds and vindicated from all material exceptions against it occasioned by a late immodest account of two conferences upon that point, between Tho. Danson and Mr. Jer. Ives, published by the said Mr. Ives, which account is also herein rectified, and its falshood detected to the just shame of the publisher / by Tho. Danson.</title>
                  <author>Danson, Thomas, d. 1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 84.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ives, Jeremiah, fl. 1653-1674.</term>
               <term>Grace (Theology)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41495:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: OR THE Saints Perſeverance Aſſerted in its poſitive Grounds, AND VINDICATED FROM ALL Material Exceptions Againſt it.</p>
            <p>OCCASIONED By a late immodeſt Account of two Conferences, upon that Point, between <hi>Tho. Danſon</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jer. Ives,</hi> Publiſhed by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Ives;</hi> Which Account is alſo herein Rectified, and its Falſhood detected, to the juſt ſhame of the PUBLISHER.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Danſon,</hi> ſometime Fellow of <hi>Magd.</hi> Coll. <hi>Oxon,</hi> and Preacher of the Word at <hi>Sandwich</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own Cauſe ſeemeth juſt, but his Neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>He that anſwereth a Matter before he heareth it, it is folly and ſhame unto him,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Verſe 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41495:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41495:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF thou art ſo judicious, as to ſee and cenſure it as a fault in me, to enter the liſts with ſuch a perſon as Mr. <hi>Ives,</hi> of whom, for the immorality of his Converſation, they are aſhamed who agree with him in Opinion. And all Chriſtians by profeſſion have cauſe to be, for his deteſtable <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> or denial of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt, which I am able ſufficiently to prove, and of which he hath never (that I know of) declared his Repentance: I willingly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſelf to thy correction; yet to excuſe what I cannot defend, thou mayeſt pleaſe to underſtand, that through the frequent inſolent Challenges of ſome of his Perſwaſion, a private Meeting was appointed for a Conference on <hi>Febr. 12. 1671.</hi> with Mr. <hi>Clayton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jennings,</hi> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer whereof undertook to defend the mortality of
<pb facs="tcp:41495:3"/>the Soul; and the latter, the poſſibility of true Believers falling away totally and finally from Grace. When we were met, Mr. <hi>Clayton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jennings</hi> both refuſed (though preſent) to diſcourſe with me: The firſt, Not aſſigning any Reaſon. The ſecond, Alledging his diſability by a Cold, and deſiring Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> might be his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute: As to the latter point, whom therefore I admitted, as knowing that ſhould I have refuſed, the man would have crowed like a Cock on his Dunghill, and his Party would have gone away ſinging, <hi>Io Triumphe.</hi> And whereas, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to agreement with Mr. <hi>Clayton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jennings,</hi> I was to oppoſe, Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> would needs make me reſpond. And very gravely read his Arguments out of his Papers, which he was ſo much beholden to, as he could not repeat any one without their aſſiſtance. And when he had done, and was deſired to change turns, and become Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent; he complaining of wearineſs, I was not unwilling to debate the Point once more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Regula</hi> being <hi>index ſui, &amp; obliqui,</hi> I thought the beſt mean, for the ſatisfaction of my Friends, at whoſe Requeſt I undertook it, were the diſcuſſing of the poſitive grounds of the Saints perſeverance. How Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> demeaned himſelf, all that know him, though abſent, can tell as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly as they that were preſent. 'Tis no News to them, that he interrupted me in the midſt of a
<pb facs="tcp:41495:3"/>Sentence, pretending he knew what I was about to ſay; nor that he made frequent Diverſions, by Addreſſes to the People, many of whom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore call'd often on him to turn about to his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt; and told him, He came not to diſpute with them, but with Mr. <hi>Danſon;</hi> nor that he would not repeat the Arguments, when he was Reſpondent, but now and then at his own liſt; and when he did, would bear me down, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, Reverend Miniſters, and private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, That my Proof was not direct to the Propoſition by him denyed; and would often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat them in words quite contrary to mine, and yet out-face us all, that he did his Opponent right. And this indeed was his carriage from firſt to laſt, more or leſs; So that it ſeems to me, either that he hath not read or not underſtood or through the <hi>freedome of his will,</hi> hath diſobeyed the Dictates of his underſtanding. That paſsage of the <hi>Publiſher of</hi> Hoard<hi>'s Gods Love to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi> in the Epiſtle to the Reader, <hi>If any ſhall uſe railing Speeches, or unneceſſary Diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the Cauſe, I ſhall ever interpret that to be a ſtrong ſign of a weak Cauſe; or at leaſt, I ſhall think it to be an argument of an obſtinate mind; who neither knoweth how to yield to the Truth, nor yet to defend his Errour.</hi> On the ſecond of <hi>March,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> wrote a Letter to me (which is ſince printed) to
<pb facs="tcp:41495:4"/>give him a meeting, that our Conferences might be publiſhed by mutual conſent, which I might well have wondered at, had not my own experience aſsur'd me, that he is <hi>more bold then wiſe;</hi> which motion I rejected, as having ſo mean an Opinion of my own Abilities, as not to think any thing of mine (much leſs ſuch a rambling Diſcourſe, as through his default that was, which I had with him) worthy of Publick View. Yet hath he publiſhed an <hi>impartial Account</hi> of our Diſcourſes, as he pretends; but whether it be ſo or no I appeal to the Notes or Memories of the Auditors, from whom I know it had been eaſie to procure a Teſtimonial; but that I judged it too great an Honour to ſuch a man as Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> is known to be, to ſuppoſe it probable, that any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet perſon ſhould take all he ſayes for Goſpel. I ſhall therefore onely requeſt any that judge it worth while, to have ſatisfaction as to matter of Fact, but to enquire of theſe Reverend Miniſters, (viz.) Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Fowler,</hi> Mr. <hi>Luffe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Parſons,</hi> Mr. <hi>Waddeſworth,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tho. Vincent,</hi> Mr. <hi>Maddox,</hi> Mr. <hi>Veal,</hi> Mr. <hi>Peachy,</hi> Mr. <hi>Charles Morton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Carſlake,</hi> [beſides others, whoſe Names at preſent occur not] and theſe ſober private Chriſtians, Mr. <hi>Summers.</hi> Mr. <hi>Farthing,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jeffreys,</hi> Inhabitants of <hi>Southwark;</hi> Mr. <hi>Parkhurſt,</hi> Mr. <hi>Anion,</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of <hi>London,</hi> [with others, too many to
<pb facs="tcp:41495:4"/>enumerate] who were preſent at one or both our Diſcourſes. And they will atteſt how often I was forced to hold my Tongue through his cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; his ſtentorian Voice drowning mine, that I could not be heard, when it was my turn to ſpeak, how often he would needs make me father his brats; I mean, acknowledge thoſe words for mine, which indeed were his own, &amp;c. The Publication of our Conferences hath laid me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a kind of neceſſity of Replying. I ſay, a <hi>kind of neceſſity,</hi> becauſe I have indeed ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt a confidence of my own Reputation, when put in competition with Mr. <hi>Ives</hi>'s, as that I could, without ſolicitude about the event, have left the World to its liberty of belief, which of us Two is the Lyar, and have thought ſilence the fitteſt Anſwer. But that which chiefly indueed me to Reply, is the opportunity put into my hands to clear up this Point of Saints perſeverence fully and ſuccinctly, in half a dozen Sheets, which none hath done that I know of in our Language; Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> hath handled the Argument in a large Quarto, Dr. <hi>Kendall</hi> and Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> in Folio. And I intend not to detract from thoſe Authors worth: But I know that the price of thoſe Books hinders the buying; and their Bulk, the reading of them by private Chriſtians, for whoſe uſe I intend this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>I have not given a particular account of all
<pb facs="tcp:41495:5"/>that was diſcourſed, but onely of what was Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative; nor indeed hath Mr. <hi>Ives,</hi> as may eaſily be judged by the bulk of his Book, compar'd with the time ſpent in the Conferences, which was no leſs then three Hours and an half in the firſt, and four Hours and an half in the ſecond; but inſtead thereof, hath, with the Bear, licked his Cubs into a better ſhape then they had at their Birth. And I therefore forbear it, becauſe I judge the World is not like to be a jot the wiſer for the knowledge of it, unleſs the ſight of rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and impertinency in their natural deformity, may deter men from ſuch unmanly Vices. But I have given a true account of all the more mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Exceptions againſt the Saints Perſeverance, and added divers Arguments for the proof of it, which I had intended to have urged, had not I been prevented. I have alſo taken notice of the Appendix, and vindicated our Doctrine from the charge of <hi>Novelty</hi> and <hi>Antinomianiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, Thou who art a true Believer, canſt not chuſe but value the Truth here contended for, and eſteem it a rich Cordial, to be aſſur'd, that though thou mayeſt loſe <hi>Florem</hi> yet thou canſt not loſe <hi>Radicem,</hi> i. e. the Flower, not the Root; the ſenſe of Grace, not Grace it ſelf; the Act not the Power: When once thou art a Member of Chriſt, there may be a benuming that may bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the influence of Blood and Spirits, but ſo as it
<pb facs="tcp:41495:5"/>ſhall never be gangren'd, it ſhall never die again; There may be a Cloud on you, but the Sun ſhall never ſet on you; to borrow the words of that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid practical Divine, Dr. <hi>Preſton, Of New Creature,</hi> Serm. <hi>5.</hi> pag. <hi>423.</hi> What a woeful caſe muſt thou needs be in, if God were onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged not to throw thee down; but not to hold thee up. The inſtances of Man's and Angels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection are too freſh in memory to be denyed; and an argument irrefragable, to evince the poſſibility of a true Believers Apoſtacy, if God ſhould be but a Spectator, and not intereſs himſelf as a party in the quarrel between him and his ſpiritual Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries. Bleſs God therefore for the immutable Purpoſes and Promiſes of being the <hi>finiſher</hi> of that Faith, whereof he hath been the <hi>Author:</hi> And if thou reapeſt any benefit by this Diſcourſe, recompence his pains by thy Prayers, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts it his Honour to be</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April 15. 1672.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>An Helper of thy joy,</hi> Tho. Danſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41495:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41495:6"/>
            <p>BEing met, Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> propoſed the Queſtion in theſe words, <hi>Whether the Doctrine of ſome true Believers, falling away totally and finally, be true?</hi> I anſwered in the Negative.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> offered to prove it thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. If the Doctrine of the impoſſibily of any true Believers falling away totally and finally from Grace be falſe, then the Doctrine of the poſſibility of ſome true Believers fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away totally and finally is true; but the former is falſe, <hi>Ergo</hi> the latter is true. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the <hi>minor,</hi> which he endeavoured to prove thus, If the Doctrine of the impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of any true Believers falling away, &amp;c. be true, then it ought to be believed. But it ought not to be believed, <hi>Ergo</hi> it is not true. I denyed the <hi>minor,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> went about to prove thus;</p>
            <p>Whatſoever ſins any are commanded not to do, and cautioned to fear the doing of, they ought not to believe is impoſſible to be done: But falling away totally and finally, is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41495:7"/>a ſin that true Believers are commanded not to do, and are cautioned to fear the doing of, <hi>Ergo</hi> true Believers ought not to believe that it is impoſſible for them to fall away totally and finally.</p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer. That many things might be objected againſt the <hi>major</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion,</hi> as that <hi>true Believers</hi> was not in the <hi>minor</hi> denyed, which he put now into his concluſion. And in his <hi>major,</hi> I told him, That we diſtinguiſhed of <hi>impoſſibility ſimple</hi> and <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute,</hi> and <hi>ex hypotheſi,</hi> or <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> of ſome other thing intervening. And that what we are cautioned to fear the doing of, may be impoſſible to be done, by reaſon of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Decree, or Promiſe, though otherwiſe poſſible, &amp;c. [All this Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> left out in his account of the Conference, and relates on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my denial of the <hi>major.</hi>] Many other things I might object, but I forbear, becauſe I would not ſeem to cavil at ſmall Faults. Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> proceeded to prove the <hi>major</hi> thus, If the Scripture no where commands the not doing, nor cautions us to fear the doing of that which is impoſſible to be done; then my <hi>major</hi> is true. But the Scripture no where commands the not doing, nor cautions us to fear the doing of that which is impoſſible to be done, <hi>Ergo</hi> my <hi>major</hi> is true. I denyed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41495:7"/>his <hi>minor;</hi> after I had firſt repeated it, Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> ſaid, It was an <hi>univerſal Negative,</hi> and therefore could not be proved. I Replyed, That it was a miſtake in him ſo to think. [And ſince our debate, it came into my mind that Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> having, 'tis like been ſometime or other on a Jury, and obſerving that a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Teſtimony in matter of Fact is not admitted (but in unuſual caſes) againſt the Affidavit; apprehends there is the like reaſon of negative Propoſition.] But however, I gave him, at his deſire, an <hi>inſtance</hi> in the <hi>ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which is impoſſible to be done by ſome to whom the Command and Caution is given, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to <hi>true Believers.</hi> To which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> Replyed, We are paſt that now, for we are out of the term, <hi>True Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers;</hi> and read over his Argument again out of his Note-Book, which it is to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for me to repeat. [The Reader may view them, I appeal to any perſon of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, whether it was not proper for me to the inſtance of the ſin, to ſubjoyn an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ſome perſons to whom it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be done, or committed.]</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> ſecond Argument was this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. If thoſe that are partakers of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature may fall away totally and finally, then ſome true Believers may fall away total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41495:8"/>and finally from Grace: But the former is true, <hi>Ergo</hi> the latter. I denyed the <hi>minor,</hi> that they who partake of the Divine Nature may fall away, ſuppoſing (I told him) that he took the phraſe in the ſenſe of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. To prove which, he argued thus;</p>
            <p>If they that are partakers of the Holy Ghoſt may fall away totally and finally, then they that are partakers of the Divine Nature may ſo fall away. But the former is true, <hi>Ergo</hi> the latter. I again denyed his conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; which he aſſayed to confirm thus, If to partake of the Holy Ghoſt, be to partake of the Divine Nature; then it follows, That if he that is partaker of the Holy Ghoſt may fall away, he that partakes of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may fall away. But the firſt is true, <hi>Ergo</hi>—</p>
            <p>I denyed his <hi>minor,</hi> which therefore he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to confirm thus, If the Nature of the Holy Ghoſt be a Divine Nature; then they that partake of the Holy Ghoſt, partake of the Divine Nature. But the former is true, <hi>Ergo</hi> the latter: I denyed his conſequence. [As for his additional Note, that to deny this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, is, <hi>As much as if a man ſhould ſay, The Wiſdom that is from above is a Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and yet ſay, That he that partakes of the Wiſdom which is from above, doth not partake
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41495:8"/>of the Divine Wiſdom.</hi> I anſwer, There's not <hi>par ratio,</hi> for that phraſe of <hi>Wiſdom from above</hi> and <hi>Divine Wiſdom</hi> note the ſame thing, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Original or Deſcent of Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>partaking of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> notes <hi>common</hi> Gifts or <hi>Graces; partaking of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, ſpecial Grace,</hi> in the places under debate.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> would prove his Conſequence, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they that partake of the Holy Ghoſt; partake of nothing elſe but what is the Divine Nature. Which I denyed, and told him, That that phraſe noted the common Gifts, whereof the Holy Ghoſt is the Author, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.3. or the extraordiary Gifts, as Tongues, &amp;c. for which I quoted, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.6.</p>
            <p>Then he proved his <hi>minor</hi> thus, Becauſe the partaking of the Holy Ghoſt and of the Divine Nature is one and the ſame thing; which I denyed, for though the receiving of the Holy Ghoſt, as to its Gifts and Graces, may be found in the ſame Subject, yet they are not terms of the ſame import; nor are the Gifts and Graces the ſame thing, any more then Logick and the Mathematicks are the ſame Art or Science, though found in the ſame Perſon; or that <hi>Bezaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiabs</hi> skill in Workmanſhip of Gold, &amp;c. And the Graces
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41495:9"/>of the Spirit, Faith, Love, &amp;c. are the ſame thing, becauſe aſcribed to the Holy Ghoſt, as their efficient. Here Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> multiplyed words to no purpoſe; as if any one would ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelf, he may find <hi>pag.</hi> 15. of his Book, and at length denyed what he had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten affirmed, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that partaking of Gifts and Graces were the ſame thing, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that they were one <hi>participation,</hi> i. e. Effects of the ſame efficient, as I underſtand his meaning; which I granted, and no Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy denies. At length he urged this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, If the Holy Ghoſt in its extraordinary Gifts be promiſed to none, but thoſe that have the ordinary Gifts and Graces of it, then none can partake of the Holy Ghoſt in the greater, that doth not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of him in the leſs: But the former is true, <hi>Ergo</hi> the latter. To the <hi>minor,</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That ſtrictly there was no <hi>promiſe</hi> of them at all, but a <hi>Prediction</hi> onely; or if we would call that, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. a Promiſe, it was to the viſible Church indefinitely, which conſiſts of viſible Believers; and many where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are only viſible. Here was a great alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation about a Promiſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, expreſly to viſible Believers; which, I told him, was not neceſſary, becauſe in promiſes of ſuch a nature
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41495:9"/>as that, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. Many might partake of the benefit that were onely viſible Believers. And that it was not ſufficient ground to judge all the perſons that had theſe extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Gifts <hi>Believers,</hi> becauſe call'd ſuch; for <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was call'd a <hi>Believer,</hi> whilſt he was not truly ſuch. [Here note a double miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>report of Mr. <hi>Ives, pag.</hi> 25, 26. That he ſayes I ſaid, <hi>Simon Magus recieved the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and that <hi>all the Promiſes are made to viſible Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers as ſuch;</hi> Whereas I ſpake onely of <hi>ſuch Promiſes,</hi> as that of <hi>Joel</hi> 2. of extraordinary but common Gifts, and that <hi>Simon Magus might have received the Holy Ghoſt in its extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Gifts, for any limitation that was in the Promiſe.</hi>] [To what I ſaid then, I ſhall onely add, That <hi>Math.</hi> 7.21, 22. and <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.4, 5. plainly enough aſſert; That thoſe that have not the ordinary Graces of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, may partake of the extraordinary Gifts of Propheſying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. If all thoſe that have the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of true Believers, mentioned in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.5, 6. may fall away totally and finally, then true Believers may fall away totally and finally; but the former is true, <hi>Ergo</hi> the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: I denyed the conſequence. [And I will now add a reaſon of it, becauſe it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds upon this ſuppoſition, that if all true
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41495:10"/>Believers are <hi>inlightned, &amp;c.</hi> then all that are inlightned are true Believers; which is as bad an argument as this, in alluſion to Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> former and preſent Trade: All the Box-Makers and Cheeſe-Mongers in the City of <hi>London</hi> are Freemen, <hi>Ergo</hi> all the Freemen in in the City of <hi>London</hi> are Box-Makers and Cheeſe-Mongers.] Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> proceeded to prove his conſequence: If all thoſe Charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be appliable to none but true Believers, then the conſequence follows: But they are appliable to none but true Believers, <hi>Ergo</hi>—</p>
            <p>I denied his <hi>minor,</hi> and demanded a proof; which he gave thus, If the Scripture applies thoſe Characters to none but true Believers, then my <hi>minor</hi> is true. But the Scripture ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies them to none but true Believers, <hi>Ergo</hi>— To which I anſwer'd, by denying his conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; for it follows not that they are not applicable to any others, becauſe they are not actually applied, [which Anſwer Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> hath omitted] and by denying the <hi>minor,</hi> whereupon he urged for an inſtance of one place of Scripture, where all theſe Charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are given to one perſon <hi>in terminis,</hi> or in the very ſame terms. To which I Replied, That the term <hi>believing,</hi> frequently applied to Perſons, not true Believers, includes all the Characters here mentioned; and that I could
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41495:10"/>ſhew him by parts where they are applied to thoſe that were not true Believers. Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> anſwered, That would not do, becauſe he that hath one Vertue may be no true Believer. I Replyed, Not as he reports my words non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſically, <hi>I take Perſons that are extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily indowed from above;</hi> But thus, That <hi>I ſpeak not of vertuous Perſons, or morally good, but of thoſe that are indued with Grace from above.</hi> After a deal of Conteſt, I inſtanced in the term <hi>inlightned,</hi> and ſhewed, That the thing intended by it, is in another term, <hi>(viz.) believing</hi> or <hi>knowing,</hi> applyed to thoſe that are not true Believers, <hi>John</hi> 17.21, 23. <hi>(viz.)</hi> to the <hi>World</hi> in this place, oppoſed to true Believers. Chriſt prays for the Converſion of thoſe that were given to him; and ſpeaks of the Conviction of the World, as an end that might be obtained thereby. I urged al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>John</hi> 1.9. Whence I urged, that that uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Light could not import a ſpiritual il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination. [The Contradiction he would faſten upon me to what I have argued from that Text againſt the <hi>Quakers, pag.</hi> 36. Of my <hi>Quakers Folly,</hi> is ſo trivial, as that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a Smile, rather then an Anſwer. Let them judge that can, by comparing that paſſage with <hi>pag.</hi> 43. and 44, 45. of Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> Book.] I alſo urged 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. compar'd with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41495:11"/>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 4.41. In the latter whereof the Devils are ſaid to know that great Doctrine, That <hi>Jeſus is the Chriſt,</hi> which in the former place is made a Character of one born of God. Whence I infer'd, that all inlightning is not a Character of a true Believer, unleſs the Devil be a true Believer. [All this explication Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> hath omitted.]</p>
            <p>The next paſſage (though not in order in the Text) which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> urged, was, <hi>renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by repentance,</hi> of the application of which paſſage to any that was not a true Believer. To which I anſwered, That it was not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to produce thoſe very terms. <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> is aſcribed to thoſe that were not true Believers, as <hi>Ahab, Judas, &amp;c.</hi> As for the phraſe <hi>renewing,</hi> that though it is frequently applyed to true Believers, yet there is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience in underſtanding it in this place, of a common work of the Spirit of God, which hath the ſame name with the ſpecial work, becauſe of ſome ſimilitude. As <hi>Saul</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>turned into another man,</hi> 1 Sam. 10.6. I urged alſo <hi>Jude</hi> 12. which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> hath barely quoted, without my gloſs on it, <hi>Trees twice dead, plucked up by the roots;</hi> in regard of their natural ſtate, which is a death in ſin, and their Apoſtacy, or looſing of what good was in them, which carried the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41495:11"/>appearance of the effects of a ſpiritual life. And <hi>plucked up by the roots,</hi> that phraſe I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned as part of the Verſe, but ſaid nothing to.</p>
            <p>The next Phraſe is, <hi>Taſting of the Powers of the World to come,</hi> of which I gave <hi>Felix</hi> for an inſtance, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25. For one part of the Powers of the World to come, is a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſenſe and apprehenſion of the future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment threatned in the Goſpel againſt Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers. [As for Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> additional Note, That <hi>taſting of the Powers of the World to come, muſt be limited to ſuch a taſte, as makes the Taſter to be in love with what he taſtes,</hi> is <hi>gratis dictum.</hi> For <hi>taſting</hi> is applyed to things evil as well as good, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. Chriſt is ſaid to <hi>taſte death.</hi> And for Mr. <hi>Ive</hi>'s fancy, that the <hi>Perſons here ſpoken of might have had ſuch a taſte</hi> (viz.) <hi>of terror, as</hi> Felix <hi>had, if they had fallen away, but not if they had not:</hi> It is a wonder to me, he ſhould forget that <hi>Felix</hi> himſelf was ſo far from having fallen away, that he did but now begin to ſtand. I mean, this terror was the firſt effect of common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions in him, and often ſeparated from any Grace at all. And 'tis much to me he ſhould be ignorant, that ſome degree of <hi>trembling at the Word</hi> is made a Character of a godly Perſon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2.] We proceeded to the <hi>taſt of the good Word of God;</hi> for inſtance whereof, I alledged
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41495:12"/>
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.20, 21. <hi>Mark</hi> 6.20. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.15 Of which places, which I onely named, that we might diſcuſs them: Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> took notice onely of the laſt, whence I obſerved, That <hi>he</hi> was tranſported with joy at the Narration which Chriſt made of the happineſs of the future State, who was a Phariſee, and to whom particularly Chriſt directed that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; The ſcope whereof is to ſhew, That they who were call'd outwardly to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of the benefits of the Goſpel, miſs'd of them, for want of a through compliance with that Call.</p>
            <p>To this Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> Replyed, <hi>That they that were bidden did not taſte of the Supper.</hi> And I rejoyned, that the not <hi>taſting,</hi> verſe 27. is conſiſtent with the <hi>taſte,</hi> which thoſe words, <hi>verſe</hi> 15. do import. For the <hi>former</hi> intends a miſſing of the benefits offer'd in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; the <hi>latter,</hi> ſome flaſhy joys in the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of a poſſible benefit. And the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Chriſt's Speech ſeems to be a tacite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probration of him, like that, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.27, 28. [Theſe Paſſages Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> hath omitted.]</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> proceeded thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. They are true Believers that have clean eſcaped the Pollutions of the World, through the knowledge of Chriſt: But ſome ſuch may fall away totally and finally, <hi>Ergo</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:41495:12"/>ſome true Believers may fall away totally and finally. To which I anſwered, That his Argument was not right in <hi>form;</hi> for he put the Subject of the Queſtion into the <hi>major,</hi> and the Predicate into the <hi>minor.</hi> His Argument ought to run thus, They that have eſcaped the Pollutions of the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may fall away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They that have eſcaped the Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are true Believers. <hi>Ergo</hi> ſome true Believers may fall away total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and finally. [I add, that if his <hi>major</hi> and <hi>minor</hi> being <hi>indefinite Propoſitions,</hi> are <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular;</hi> then the Syllogiſm is falſe, according to the old Rule, <hi>Syllogizari non eſt ex particulari.</hi>]</p>
            <p>If they be <hi>univerſal,</hi> then by a ſimple con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the minor, (the terms being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertible according to his ſenſe) from thoſe premiſes may an univerſal Affirmative be rightly deduced (which he all along declin'd), thus the Argument ſtands in the firſt Figure, All that have eſcaped the Pollutions of the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may fall away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers have eſcaped the Pollutions of the World, <hi>&amp;c. Ergo</hi> all true Believers may fall away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At length, not knowing how to mend the form, though I directed him, he put his Syllogiſm into an Hypoth. form; If thoſe that have clean eſcaped the Pollutions,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41495:13"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as before) may fall away, then true Believers may fall away: But ſuch may, <hi>Ergo</hi> true Believers may. I denyed the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, becauſe to eſcape the Pollutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is not a Deſcription onely of true Believers: Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> attempted to prove it, becauſe that <hi>quality</hi> [<hi>qualification,</hi> I ſuppoſe, he would have ſaid] is applicable to none but true Believers; which being denyed, he proved thus; If that quality be applicable to any but true Believers, then either to Hypocrites, or prophane Perſons; But to neither, <hi>Ergo</hi>—</p>
            <p>To his <hi>minor,</hi> I anſwered, That it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to Hypocrites: Againſt which An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> urged, That if ſo, then an Hypocrite may be free from the Pollutions of the World, in the midſt of his Hypocriſie; which I granted, in the ſenſe of the Text un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der debate, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20. Then he urged, that if ſo, Hypocriſie is not a Pollution of the World: I denyed the Connexion, becauſe 'tis meant but of groſs Pollutions, that theſe perſons had eſcaped: And that the terms be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indefinite, [and <hi>in materia contingenti,</hi> which Clauſe Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> hath left out, as not underſtanding it, I know,] they were but particular, not of all, but ſome Pollutions, which a perſon may be free from, whilſt he is tainted with others. Then Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> call'd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41495:13"/>for a Greek Teſtament, to ſee what the Greek word is, that is rendred <hi>clean,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. [Note, though it be no matter of moment, but to ſhew the fidelity of Mr. <hi>Ive</hi>'s Report. Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> ſayes, a Friend of mine pull'd out a Greek Teſtament, and read the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and rendred it as he had done before <hi>really,</hi> or <hi>truly;</hi> whereas upon Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> calling for a Greek Teſtament, and my Friend, an ingenious young Schollar, Mr. <hi>Glaſcock</hi> tendring it me, I ſaid, it needed not, for I remembred the word, and its ſignification.] Then Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> call'd for an <hi>inſtance,</hi> I gave him that of the Phariſees, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11, 12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which he anſwer'd, That they that were neither juſt, merciful nor faithful, were not free from the groſs Pollutions of the World. To which I Replyed, That what ever they did contrary to the Laws of Mercy, Juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they did with ſuch cunning, that it did not appear to the World. For it could not be imagin'd, that Chriſt ſhould affirm, that thoſe perſons were outwardly righteous, as he does <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.28. who were openly and viſibly guilty of ſuch Miſcarriages.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> Replyed, That thoſe men, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20. had eſcaped from thoſe that lived in Error; and how could that be, if they lived in the greateſt Error, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Hypocriſie. I
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41495:14"/>rejoyned, that they could not at the ſame be guilty of Hypocriſie, and yet free from it; but they might be intangled in Hypocriſie, and yet freed from external groſs ſins. Again, that 'tis not ſaid, they were <hi>clean eſcaped from Error,</hi> but <hi>from them that lived in Error,</hi> i. e. changed their Company, or ſorted with Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, which they might do, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Hypocrites. Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> demanded, how then <hi>their latter end could be worſe then their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</hi> I anſwer'd, Becauſe open Sins do openly diſhonor Chriſtianity; whence <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> wiſhed, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam omnes eſſent Hypocritae, Would to God all men were Hypocrites.</hi> [This paſſage, with ſome others immediately before, Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> hath omitted.] As to Mr. <hi>Ive</hi>'s <hi>additional Note,</hi> that <hi>Hypocrites cannot be in a worſe condition, by appearing openly prophane.</hi> I Anſwer, They may, not only becauſe of the open diſhonour done to Religion, but becauſe alſo their profaneneſs is a Sin againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and ſo adds weight to their Chains, and heats their Furnace hotter. See <hi>James</hi> 4.17. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.47. For though Hypocriſie ſingly may be worſe then profaneneſs in ſome reſpects, yet the profaneneſs of an Hypocrite is the worſt profaneneſs. At length, I gave <hi>Paul</hi> for an inſtance, of one that had eſcaped the Pollutions of the World, whilſt yet he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41495:14"/>was an Hypocrite <hi>(viz.)</hi> before he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. About which many words were ſpent; the ſum was, that either he was a true Believer, or Profane, or an Hypocrite: Not the firſt, for we ſuppoſe him unconverted; nor the ſecond, as appears <hi>Acts</hi> 26.5. <hi>Ergo</hi> the third, [all which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> omits] which I proved from the Character given of the Body of the Jews, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.31, 32. and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by himſelf, as agreeing to him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7. <hi>(viz.)</hi> that they mixed their own Righteouſneſs with the <hi>Meſſiah</hi>'s, whom, as to come, they profeſſed to believe in. And to what Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> Objected, That <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, He did what he did with an honeſt mind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Converſion, and ſo was no Hypocrite. I anſwer'd, There might be a moral integrity in an unconverted perſon, alledging, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.5, 6. <hi>Abimelech,</hi> an Heathen, and diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Hypocrites; that though all agree in having an appearance of that Grace which they want, yet <hi>ſome</hi> deſign to appear what they neither are, nor care to be; others are miſtaken in themſelves, and make account they are what they are not, for which latter I quoted <hi>James</hi> 1.22, 26. And of this latter ſort was <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:41495:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. And laſt, was this, grounded on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27. what <hi>Paul</hi> uſed all diligence to prevent the coming to paſs of, might poſſibly come to paſs: But <hi>Paul</hi> uſed all diligence to prevent his falling away totally and finally, <hi>Ergo</hi> his falling away totally and finally was poſſible to come to paſs. I anſwer'd to his <hi>major,</hi> that which is poſſible in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, there being a real hazzard in the nature of the thing, may yet become impoſſible as to the event, by ſomething intervening. To which he Replyed nothing, but asked me, whether <hi>Paul</hi> knew this event impoſſible? I affirmed it, whereupon he urged, that then it was in vain for him to keep himſelf out of the danger. And I Replyed, That it was not in vain, becauſe God hath in his Decree joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the end and means, and the Command of God is obeyed, which ſure is a good end propoſed by us in the uſe of means, though we might ſuppoſe the benefit obtainable with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that uſe. To confirm the former branch of my Anſwer, I inſtanced in Gods Promiſe, of lengthening out <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> life fifteen years, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.5. and yet obliging him to uſe a Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Figs to cure his Boyl, <hi>verſe</hi> 25. A wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Miniſter Mr. <hi>Luffe,</hi> who now and then (as Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> ſayes) interpoſed, to diſcover his abſurd method of arguing, alledged that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41495:15"/>other inſtance of <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 27.22, 31. And whereas Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> ſuppoſes Mr. <hi>Luffes</hi> Anſwer to his Queſtion, what if they had leapt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board? <hi>(viz.)</hi> that then they had been drowned, a granting of what was contended for; the contrary is evident, by what is ſaid above. We concluded all, with another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tepretation of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, rendred in our Tranſlations <hi>a caſt away;</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies alſo <hi>diſapproved,</hi> or <hi>blame-worthy,</hi> for not practiſing his own Doctrine. Here Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> kept a great pudder, that either my firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of being <hi>a caſt-away</hi> [which yet I did not ſo interpret, but conceded his interpretation of it, as not hurting our Cauſe,] was true or falſe; if true, why did I not keep to it? if falſe, why did I alledge it? And makes an additional Note, that by this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, I grant his <hi>major.</hi> To his Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I anſwered, That I conceded the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, becauſe our Engliſh Tranſlation was defenſible. And yet I alledged the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as being warranted by the Greek, and taking off any Argument from thence by his Party. And to his <hi>additional Note,</hi> I Anſwer, That if I had at firſt interpreted the Greek word <hi>diſapproved,</hi> or <hi>blame-worthy;</hi> then I would not have denyed his <hi>major,</hi> what <hi>Paul</hi> uſed all diligence to prevent, might come to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41495:16"/>paſs, but his <hi>minor, (viz.)</hi> But <hi>Paul</hi> uſed all diligence to prevent his falling away totally and finally. I ſhould have ſaid, that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the line of this interpretation, <hi>Paul</hi> uſed diligence to walk ſo, as not to diſpleaſe God, nor be a ſhame to that Goſpel, of which he was not aſhamed. What Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> hath got by this Note, he may put in his Eyes, and ſee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the worſe. [End of the firſt Conference.]</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>HAving finiſhed my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Ive</hi>'s Arguments, for the Saints falling away totally and finally from Grace: I ſhall add other Arguments, which the <hi>Arminians</hi> urge, for the confirmation thereof. The firſt Scripture I ſhall reply to, is <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.24, 25. <hi>But when the Righteous turneth away from his righteouſneſs, and committeth iniquity, and doth according to all the abominatious that the wicked man doth, ſhall he live? &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which place we except in general.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exc.</hi> 1. That the righteous man here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of is not a <hi>truly righteous man,</hi> or <hi>true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever,</hi> nor does what they produce for proof obtain its end.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That he is oppoſed to a wicked man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> So is the <hi>Righteous</hi> to <hi>Sinners, Math.</hi> 9.13. <hi>I am not come</hi> (ſayes Chriſt) <hi>to call the Righteous, but Sinners to repentance;</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41495:16"/>which is ſpoken of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> verſe 11. who did outwardly appear righteous unto men, <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.28. which outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance was ground enough for that denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That the wicked man whom <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaks of, was truly wicked; therefore the righteous man he ſpeaks of muſt be truly righteous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply</hi> 1. <hi>Math.</hi> 9.13. Before alledged, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers this Argument: The Publicans and Sinners <hi>(viz.)</hi> open debauched Perſons, were truly <hi>Sinners;</hi> yet were not the Phariſees tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly righteous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 2. We retort upon them, that the Text ſpeaking of a wicked man, as <hi>viſibly wicked,</hi> therefore the righteous man may be underſtood of him that is <hi>viſibly righteous</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; Such as <hi>Paul,</hi> whilſt a Phariſee, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6. And ſo the Antitheſis is more direct, and the Deſcription here given of a righteous man, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The forbearance of external groſs acts of Sin, Idolatry, Adultery, <hi>&amp;c. Ezek.</hi> 18.6, 7. And the doing of external acts of Mercy, Juſtice, <hi>verſe</hi> 8, 9. ſufficiently favours our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Excep.</hi> 2. is this, That the Death here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, is but a <hi>Temporal Death, [immediately</hi> and <hi>explicitly.</hi>]</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41495:17"/>
               <p>The reaſon of this our aſſertion is, becauſe the Lord does evidently vindicate himſelf from the imputation caſt upon him by the wicked Jews, that in their Publick Calamities, he exceeded the deſert of their perſonal Sins, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.2, 19, 25, 29. So we muſt underſtand thoſe Complaints, for we do not find that they charge him with caſting them into Hell for their Fathers ſins; nor is there any weight in what the <hi>Arminians</hi> urge, for extending the phraſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Death here ſpoken of, is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the life promiſed to the Penitent; which is eternal life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply</hi> 1. The <hi>Arminians</hi> here forſake their own Principle, which is, that there's no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Promiſe of eternal life in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though we deny not, but that eternal life in Old Teſtament and New is promiſed to the Penitent; yet we deny that by <hi>life here,</hi> is meant at leaſt <hi>immediately</hi> and <hi>expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly eternal life,</hi> but onely <hi>temporal;</hi> for God ſpeaks <hi>ad idem,</hi> as of the ſame Death the Jews complain'd of, ſo of the ſame life they were deſirous of.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That then a flagitious Sinner may eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape eternal Death without Repentance.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:41495:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> We deny the Conſequence, becauſe though this Scripture does not explicitly threaten eternal Death to ſuch a Sinner, yet other Scriptures do, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Except.</hi> 3. We except againſt their poſition from a ſuppoſition, that by the righteous man, were meant a truly righteous man; that therefore it is ſimply poſſible, that a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man ſhould totally and finally depart from his righteouſneſs, and die eternally. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. When Chriſt ſayes, <hi>If a man abide not in me, he is caſt forth as a branch, and is wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp;c.</hi> John 15.6. That conditional enun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation does not imply a ſimple poſſibility of the antecedent and conſequent <hi>(viz.)</hi> of the total and final Apoſtacy, and damnation of all the men that are in Chriſt; for of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Chriſt ſayes, <hi>I have choſen you, and ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, that you ſhould go and bring forth fruit, and that your Fruit ſhould remain,</hi> verſe 16. <hi>And I appoint unto you a Kingdom, as my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath appointed unto me,</hi> Luke 22.29.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We cannot ſuppoſe a greater poſſibility of the Antecedent and Conſequent in this Enunciation; <hi>If the Righteous turn away from his righteouſneſs, he ſhall die,</hi> then in this, <hi>If the Wicked turn away from his wickedneſs, he ſhall live.</hi> But from this conditional Enun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41495:18"/>cannot be inferr'd a ſimple poſſibility of the converſion of all wicked men, and of their Salvation; the <hi>Arminians</hi> themſelves being Judges: For if ſo, then Gods preſcience of the final impenitency and perdition of ſome wicked men muſt needs be denied, which yet in their good moods the <hi>Arminians</hi> ſtick not to grant. <hi>Vide Ameſ. Anti Synodalia,</hi> Art. 5. c. 2.</p>
               <p>Another Scripture urged by the <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> is, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.20, 21. Whence they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That theſe Perſons have a Deſcription given of them, agreeing to true Believers; 1. That they receive or believe the Word. 2. With gladneſs, 3. They profeſs the Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To the parts of the Deſcription.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Believing is aſcribed to the Devil, of this truth, That there is a God, <hi>James</hi> 2.19. And this, That Jeſus is the Chriſt, and Son of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.41. Which belief is elſe-where made an evidence of a new Birth, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. By the collation of which places, we rightly conclude, That every believing does not denominate men true Believers. For if the Devils believing be not true Faith, why ſhould every believing of Mens? yea, the Scripture tells us, that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> believed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41495:18"/>and that at the ſame time his heart was not right in the ſight of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13, 21. See alſo <hi>John</hi> 2.23, 24.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To the ſecond we have ſpoken already, in anſwer to <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To the third, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.41. may ſuffice, where the Devil openly profeſſes the Faith, as well as ſecretly believes it. See alſo <hi>Acts</hi> 16.17. Where the Devil openly acknowledges the Goſpel, to be <hi>the way of Salvation.</hi> And <hi>Acts</hi> 19.15. he owns Chriſt's Authority over him, as the Lord, and <hi>Pauls</hi> as the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When yet the Apoſtle tells us, That <hi>no man can ſay, that Jeſus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.3. Whence I infer, that every Profeſſion is not an <hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium,</hi> or mark of true Faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Arminians</hi> obſerve, That the ſtony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground-Hearers were not Hypocrites, and therefore true Believers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have ſpoken to this before; we diſtinguiſh in the Antecedent of Hypocrites; <hi>Some</hi> are not, nor care to be, what yet they would be taken for; in that ſenſe we grant their Antecedent: <hi>Others</hi> eſteem themſelves what they are not, ſo we deny their Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. In this laſt ſenſe they were Hypocrites, which is evident, becauſe 'tis ſaid, they had <hi>no root</hi> in a tropical term, and are oppoſed to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41495:19"/>a <hi>good and honeſt heart</hi> (which is the explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that term) which only the laſt ſort had, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.21. compared with <hi>Luke</hi> 8.15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Arminians</hi> affirm, That perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is not of the eſſence of true Faith; and therefore theſe Perſons might have true Faith, though they fell away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We diſtinguiſh in the Antecedent between that which is of the eſſence of true Faith, <hi>Conſtitutivè</hi> and <hi>Conſecutivè,</hi> i. e. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that which is an eſſential part of true Faith, and an adjunct or Property inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from it, <hi>Ex hypotheſi cauſe efficientis exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae,</hi> upon ſuppoſition of ſome external effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſes of operation. Thus the Moon ſuffers an Eclipſe alway, when the Earth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſes between the Sun and it. Thus ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing a continual influence of Grace, which God hath decreed, and promiſed to afford (as we have proved) to true Faith; perſeverance is a neceſſary adjunct of it.</p>
               <p>Another Scripture alledged by the <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns,</hi> is <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. <hi>Now the Juſt ſhall live by Faith; but if any man draw back my Soul ſhall have no pleaſure in him:</hi> Where they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That we put <hi>any man</hi> inſtead of <hi>he, i. e.</hi> the <hi>juſt man,</hi> as they interpret it, the Greek being <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and they charge <hi>Beza,</hi> and others, that wrote in Latine and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41495:19"/>our Engliſh Tranſlations, with unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. In ſome of our Engliſh Bibles, the words <hi>any man</hi> are put into a <hi>ſmall Letter,</hi> to note they are not in the Text. In the Tranſlation before King <hi>James,</hi> now in uſe, the word <hi>any</hi> without <hi>man,</hi> is put in a ſmaller Letter, as in an Edition in Quarto, printed by <hi>Barker,</hi> A. D. 1603. And <hi>Piſcater</hi> puts <hi>quis</hi> in a Diſtinguiſhing Character, <hi>Edit. Herb. Naſſ.</hi> 1613. And ſo does <hi>Beza</hi> in all the Editions of his Verſions that I have met with, which ſhews plainly they intended not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. <hi>Calvin</hi> renders it to their mind, <hi>Si ſubductus fuerit, If he ſhall be withdrawn, or drawn back;</hi> though he underſtands the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtle otherwiſe then the <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> do.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There muſt be a ſupply of <hi>quis,</hi> or <hi>any man.</hi> For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. How can the <hi>juſt draw back,</hi> if he <hi>lives by Faith.</hi> I am ſure Chriſt ſayes, That he that eats him, (which ſurely every Believer does) <hi>ſhall live for ever,</hi> John 6.51, 58.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If it be meant of the ſame perſon, then we may underſtand it of a <hi>partial</hi> and <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary drawing back,</hi> which diſpleaſes God, as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Davids</hi> Murther and Adultery, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41495:20"/>
               <p n="3">3. The Apoſtles confidence of the not drawing back, and ſalvation of ſome that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>verſe laſt.</hi> Though it was grounded but upon Charity, as to particular Perſons, yet it plainly intimates a difference between Faith and Faith; or otherwiſe he had no ground for his confidence of any Believer at all.</p>
               <p>We now proceed to the Inſtances which the <hi>Arminians</hi> give us of thoſe Perſons that did fall away totally or finally, one or both from true Grace: Their firſt inſtance is of <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> True Believers, when they commit Adultery, Murther, againſt the light of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, with deliberation, and continue therein without Repentance, ceaſe to be true Believers: But ſo did <hi>David, Ergo</hi> he ceaſed to be a true Believer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is an ambiguity in the terms of the <hi>major,</hi> which therefore muſt firſt be removed; and as 'tis phraſed, we deny it, and anſwer to the <hi>minor</hi> with diſtinction.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For committing thoſe Sins againſt the <hi>light of Conſcience,</hi> we diſtinguiſh of an <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> and <hi>actual light of Conſcience.</hi> 'Tis a Rule in moral Philoſophy, <hi>Omnis incontinens peccat ignorans,</hi> i. e. <hi>Every incontinent perſon ſins ignorantly,</hi> becauſe that general know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41495:20"/>he hath of evil, he cannot apply to the preſent reſiſtance of temptation, (inward Luſts, like a Cloud, or Miſt, darkning his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding for the preſent.) Thus we grant the former, but deny the latter of <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. As to ſmning with <hi>deliberation,</hi> we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between a <hi>Calm</hi> and <hi>perfect,</hi> or a <hi>diſturbed</hi> and <hi>imperfect deliberation.</hi> The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer we deny, but the latter we grant of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> For we have proved before, under the firſt Argument, againſt Believers Apoſtacy, that no Believer ſins with full conſent of will, and therefore not with a calm and perfect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation; for the former preſuppoſes this latter. And we may retort the <hi>Arminians</hi> own conceſſion upon them, which is, <hi>That the holy Spirit is not loſt, till after the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of heinous Sins:</hi> Now where the holy Spirit is, <hi>it luſts againſt the Fleſh,</hi> Gal. 5.17. And conſequently the true Believer cannot ſin with full conſent, whilſt the holy Spirit is in him; that is, whilſt he is a true Believer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As to the continuance in ſin without Repentance, we diſtinguiſh between an <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> and <hi>actual Repentance;</hi> and again, between the want of <hi>actual Repentance for a time,</hi> and <hi>for ever</hi> after the Fact committed. Whilſt <hi>David</hi> wanted an actual Repentance, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears not that he wanted an habitual Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41495:21"/>
                  <hi>David</hi> might have ſuch a diſpoſition of Soul at that time, which at other times he words after this manner, <hi>Cleanſe thou me from ſecret faults,</hi> Pſal. 19.12. Let them that deny it, make proof of their denial; but to ſave them the trouble, I will evince the Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative by and by. Again, it is not evident from Scripture, that actual Repentance muſt immediately follow the ſin committed; or for default thereof, Grace totally loſt. I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, why <hi>the Believer</hi> as well as <hi>the man</hi> may not ſuffer a <hi>deliquium,</hi> or failure, of the more ordinary ſenſible operations of life, and yet retain the principle of life.</p>
               <p>There are alſo two Arguments drawn from the nature of the ſins <hi>David</hi> was guilty of, for the proof of his total Apoſtacy.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For his Adultery, <hi>David,</hi> by his Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, was made a member of an Harlot. <hi>Ergo</hi> he was no longer a Member of Chriſt. The Antecedent is proved from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15, 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We deny the Connexion: For as in the Conjugal ſtate, Adultery does make void the Marriage-Covenant <hi>de jure,</hi> or <hi>merito,</hi> not <hi>de facto;</hi> but the injured Party may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the band, without guilt of Adultery. So though Chriſt might juſtifie a Divorce, yet it appears not that he will ſue out one
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41495:21"/>againſt any Believer that is guilty of bodily Adultery.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another Argument of the <hi>Arminians,</hi> is drawn from <hi>Davids Murther, No Murtherer hath eternal life abiding in him: David</hi> was a Murtherer, <hi>Ergo</hi> he had not eternal life abiding in him. The <hi>major</hi> proved by the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.15. The <hi>minor</hi> they take for granted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We deny the <hi>minor, David</hi> was not a Murtherer, that denomination could not be given him from a ſingle Act, and afterwards repented of; any more then the denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a <hi>wicked man</hi> to a true Believer, becauſe of the Sins he is guilty of.</p>
               <p>Another Argument of the <hi>Arminians</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Davids</hi> perſeverance, is drawn from his Prayer, <hi>Create in me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me,</hi> Pſal. 51.10. Whence they infer, That he had loſt a clean Heart, and right Spirit, <hi>totally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This (as generally what the <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> urge on the Point before us) is a pitty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fallacy, which every freſhman in the School is acquainted with, <hi>à Dicto ſecundum quid, ad dictum ſimpliciter.</hi> They might as well infer from the Evangeliſts phraſe, <hi>For the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given,</hi> John 7.39. That therefore <hi>David</hi> never had him at all.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41495:22"/>All know, that in nature that ſpecies of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion call'd <hi>Alteratio,</hi> which is a change made in a Subject as to quality, may be either <hi>quoad ſpeciem</hi> or <hi>gradum.</hi> As water quite cold may become lukewarm, or ſeething hot.</p>
               <p>And here <hi>David</hi> might well expreſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo emphatically, becauſe of the late ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary defilement he had contracted, and the quick ſence he had of it at this time.</p>
               <p>To cloſe up the Diſcourſe of this inſtance, I ſhall offer two Arguments to prove, that <hi>David</hi> did not wholly fall from Grace.</p>
               <p>One from Pſalm 51. <hi>Take not the holy Spirit from me,</hi> verſe 11. His deprecation of the taking away the holy Spirit, does plainly imply a gradual preſence of it. For that could not be taken from him, which he had not.</p>
               <p>The other from Pſalm 18.21. <hi>I have not wickedly departed from my God:</hi> Whence I urge an Argument in form, He that had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wickedly departed from God, had never fallen away totally from Grace.</p>
               <p>But <hi>David</hi> had never wickedly departed from God, <hi>Ergo, David</hi> had never fallen away totally from Grace.</p>
               <p>The <hi>major</hi> I preſume they deny not: The <hi>minor</hi> I ſuppoſe will not down with them, becauſe they may imagine, that this was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41495:22"/>before his total Apoſtacy. But to me 'tis evident, That <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks this of himſelf, after the ſuppoſed time of his total Apoſtacy. For it was ſpoken after God had delivered him from the hands of all his Enemies, as appears by the <hi>Title</hi> of the Pſalm, and he takes notice particularly of Gods <hi>delivering him from the ſtrivings of his People,</hi> (i. e. his own Subjects) <hi>verſe</hi> 43. which evidently relates to the Rebellion of <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Sheba,</hi> which were after, and a puniſhment of thoſe Sins of <hi>David</hi> (by which the <hi>Arminians</hi> pretend he fell away totally from Grace) as any one may inform himſelf, that will compare 2 <hi>Sam. Chap.</hi> 11.12. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.10. with <hi>Chap.</hi> 15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the 20th. And when thoſe Sins were committed, <hi>David</hi> was in actual conteſt with his Enemies, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if in any ſin <hi>David</hi> had <hi>wickedly departed from God,</hi> we may judge in that, by the black brand which the Holy Ghoſt ſets upon that, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.5.</p>
               <p>Another inſtance is of <hi>Solomon,</hi> from whoſe Idolatry, and other Sins, they infer his total Apoſtacy, and final too, and ſo conſequently his Damnation, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. As to his <hi>Idolatry,</hi> not every de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of that ſin argues a defection from true Grace, as is evident by <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.5, 25. in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41495:23"/>the inſtance of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20, 21, 22. And as for <hi>Polygamy,</hi> Cuſtom had ſo blinded mens eyes, that few ſaw the evil of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. There's no Sin (except that againſt the Holy Ghoſt) which a Child of God may not be guilty of, becauſe the body of Sin is not dead, though deadly wounded; but like a ſick man, ever and anon giving ground for a belief, that his recovery is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>But that he was not a total Apoſtate, or ceaſed to be a Believer; We argue thus,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that all the Writers of the Holy Scripture are ſimply affirmed to be <hi>holy Men of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. whereof <hi>Solomon</hi> was one.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe he is ſaid to be loved of God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.24. Now the love of God is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, <hi>John</hi> 13.1.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Solomon</hi> was not a final Apoſtate, we prove thus,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that he repented of his Miſcarriages, as appears by the Title, <hi>The Penitent,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> [of which word and thing, the learned may find uſeful Obſervations amaſs'd by Mr. <hi>Pool,</hi> in his <hi>Synopſis Crit. Comm. in Eccleſ.</hi> 1.] Given to <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> (as our Tranſlation calls it) and particularly of giving himſelf to Women, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.26. under which, and that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41495:23"/>phraſe of <hi>Inventions, verſe ult.</hi> he ſeems to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude his <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which, for ought appears to me, was not by perſonal worſhip, but by connivance at, or at moſt, allowance of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for his Wives Idolatrous Worſhip, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.7, 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From his being joyned with <hi>David,</hi> as a Preſident for <hi>Rehoboams</hi> walking, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.17.</p>
               <p>Many other Arguments, <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> might be produced, but it is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; theſe have much more probability then the Scriptures ſilence of his Repentance, (which is the <hi>Arminians</hi> main Argument); No Scriptures mention <hi>Noahs, Lots, &amp;c.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of thoſe heinous Sins, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19. yet none doubt, or have ground at leaſt, of their Repentance.</p>
               <p>A third inſtance is given in <hi>Peter,</hi> whom, though <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſpeaks favourably of, as to total Apoſtacy, <hi>De Rom. Pontif. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Perdidit confeſſionem Fidei, non ipſam fidem.</hi> Yet the Lutherans, <hi>Hinckelman, Hunnius, &amp;c.</hi> give him for another inſtance of true Believers falling totally from Grace.</p>
               <p>Their firſt Argument is drawn from the nature of his Sin, <hi>(viz.) a denial of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that denies Chriſt before Men, ſhall be denied by Chriſt before the Father, [which
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41495:24"/>propoſition is contained <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.33.] But ſo did <hi>Peter, Ergo</hi> he ſhall be denied by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. In general, this Argument, if it were wholly granted them, proves his <hi>final Apoſtacy,</hi> which themſelves deny (as we ſhall find in their next Argument.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. We Anſwer. The propoſition is to be underſtood of a <hi>final denial</hi> of Chriſt; and then we deny the <hi>minor,</hi> for <hi>Peter</hi> quickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of his denial, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. <hi>ult.</hi> To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force their <hi>major,</hi> the <hi>Arminians</hi> urge, The denial of Chriſt was an Hereſie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore puts the Denyer into a ſtate of Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We diſtinguiſh of Hereſie, 'tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered either <hi>materially</hi> or <hi>formally:</hi> To the latter, pertinacy or <hi>obſtinacy</hi> is a neceſſary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient, which <hi>Peter</hi>'s ſpeedy Repentance aſſures us he was not guilty of.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Arminians</hi> ſecond Argument is this, He that was to be converted anew to the Faith, had loſt the Faith he had: But <hi>Peter</hi> was to be converted anew to the Faith, <hi>Ergo</hi> he had loſt the Faith he had. The <hi>minor</hi> is proved by <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We diſtinguiſh in the <hi>minor</hi> between a <hi>ſpecifical</hi> and a <hi>gradual</hi> Converſion: A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery from prevailing Sin is call'd <hi>Converſion,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41495:24"/>Matth.</hi> 18.3. which is ſpoken of adding to all their other Graces that of Humility, for they were converted before. And the reaſon of this denomination is, becauſe <hi>The increaſe of Grace is by adding a new degree of Grace; as in making Candles, when a Candle is put anew into the fat of boyled Tallow, every time it is put in, it comes out bigger. And this is done by a new act of Creation put forth by God, &amp;c.</hi> To borrow the Reaſon, and apt Similitude for the illuſtration of it, of that <hi>moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Divine Dr. Tho. Goodwin, Trial of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian growth, pag.</hi> 165.</p>
               <p>But that <hi>Peter</hi> did not fall away <hi>totally,</hi> is evident from <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Prayer, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32. (which, that it is always anſwered, hath been proved) which muſt be meant either <hi>not at all</hi> (which the event aſſures us was not <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s meaning) or not <hi>totally,</hi> or <hi>finally,</hi> which laſt the words will not bear.</p>
               <p>A fourth Inſtance is of the <hi>Galatians, ch.</hi> 5.4. whence they argue thus, The <hi>Galatians</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell from Grace: The <hi>Galatians</hi> were true Believers. <hi>Ergo,</hi> True Believers have fallen from Grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If the <hi>major</hi> or <hi>minor</hi> being inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, be equivalent to an Univerſal, we deny <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem both.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To the <hi>major</hi> we ſay, That by falling
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41495:25"/>from Grace, is not meant falling from true inherent Grace, but the <hi>Doctrine of Grace,</hi> or the truth of the Goſpel, which teaches Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by Grace through Faith, not by Works, as ſeemes evident by comparing the Phraſe elſewhere, oppoſed to <hi>another Gopel,</hi> which ſuppoſes <hi>Grace</hi> to be <hi>one Goſpel, Gal.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               <p>A fifth, of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19, 20. whence they argue,</p>
               <p>They that have put away Faith and a good Conſcience, are totally and finally fallen away from Grace: But ſo had <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander: Ergo,</hi> They were fallen away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We diſtinguiſh in the <hi>minor,</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>a God Conſcience.</hi> There is a <hi>feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Faith,</hi> as the Apoſtles denomination, <hi>Faith unfeigned, v.</hi> 5. imports: And there is a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience morally good. Abimelech,</hi> an Heathen, gives teſtimony to the <hi>integrity</hi> of his <hi>own heart, Gen.</hi> 20.5. and God himſelf confirms it, <hi>v.</hi> 6. Yet <hi>integrity,</hi> or uprightneſs of heart, is the uſual deſcription of a godly man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.2.</p>
               <p>All that is worth the tranſcribing, which the <hi>Arminians</hi> urge to confirm their <hi>minor,</hi> is this:</p>
               <p>That which <hi>Timothy</hi> was exhorted to hold or keep, <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> had loſt:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41495:25"/>But that was a true Faith, and truly good Conſcience: <hi>Ergo, Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> had loſt ſuch a Faith and Conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We grant the whole, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to our cauſe, limiting the <hi>major</hi> to that which was <hi>viſible;</hi> for ſo <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> had loſt what <hi>Timothy</hi> was exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to keep, as appears by their <hi>blaſphemy, ver. laſt.</hi> which was a viſible caſting off their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
               <p>The laſt Example of <hi>Demas,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. if put into form, runs thus: Some love of the World is inconſiſtent with true Faith: Some love of the World was in <hi>Demas: Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, Demas</hi>'s love to the World was inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with true Faith. An evidently infirm Ratiocination: <hi>Vid. Ames Antiſyn. de Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Sanct. c.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Arminians</hi> Argument, from the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities following from our <hi>Theſis,</hi> is this in general, That it renders Exhortations, Threatnings, Promiſes, uſeleſs.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, The <hi>firſt are not uſeleſs, Phil.</hi> 2.12, 13. For the aſſurance of ſo powerful an Aſſiſtance, is the greateſt ſpur to endeavour. The <hi>Arminians</hi> might with as much reaſon ſay, It is to no purpoſe to hoiſe up the Sails, when God ſends a fair Wind. Nor the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond:</hi> For 1. All true Believers know not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41495:26"/>their own ſafety. 2. God hath joyned the uſe of means and end together, by an immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Decree; ſo that if we could ſuppoſe a true Believer to give over in his race, he would certainly miſs of his Crown. Nor the <hi>third:</hi> For the ſpirit of a Chriſtian being an ingenuous ſpirit, the aſſurance of his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, is the greateſt bond of gratitude and obedience. <hi>Much more I might ſay; but this is enough.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:41495:26"/>
            <head>THE Second Conference.</head>
            <p>HEre Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> firſt read out of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per a kind of Explication of the Terms; wherein he dealt like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>diſingenuouſly,</hi> and <hi>ignorantly: The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> in that he would underſtand the Term <hi>Grace</hi> of the <hi>Favour of God,</hi> which none of us do; and his former Arguments ſhew, he took it not ſo himſelf, but for the <hi>Grace of God in us,</hi> the effect of the Grace or Favour of God: <hi>The latter,</hi> in the explication of the word <hi>impoſſible,</hi> as <hi>oppoſed to ſuch as either have, may, might, or can fall away:</hi> For <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible</hi> is oppoſed to <hi>poſſible;</hi> and he ought to have diſtinguiſhed between that which is <hi>ſimply impoſſible,</hi> and that which is ſo <hi>in a certain reſpect,</hi> according to my Anſwer when I was Reſpondent; and have told us, That he held it ſimply or abſolutely poſſible for true Believers to loſe their Grace totally and finally.</p>
            <p>And in the proſecution of the Debate, I firſt offered to retort his own Arguments,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41495:27"/>which were reducible to two Heads: 1. From the uſeleſneſs of caution againſt falling away, if it were impoſſible: 2. From Examples. Neither of which he would admit me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort, but by his rude clamor forced me to deſiſt, before he heard me out an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I ſhall therefore now give an account of what I then intended to urge.</p>
            <p>That which makes not the giving of Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion needleſs to prevent temporal death; makes it not needleſs to prevent falling away totally and finally from Grace: But the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of the event makes it not needleſs in the former, <hi>Ergo,</hi> nor in the latter caſe. The <hi>major</hi> depends upon the <hi>par ratio</hi> between temporal and ſpiritual death. The <hi>minor</hi> I would have proved thus: That which makes not the uſe of Caution needleſs to prevent temporal death, makes not the giving of it needleſs: But the impoſſibility of the event makes not the uſe of it needleſs, <hi>&amp;c. Ergo,</hi> nor the giving of it. The <hi>minor</hi> I would have proved by <hi>John</hi> 11.54, 55. compared with <hi>John</hi> 13.1. and <hi>chap.</hi> 10.18. where we find that <hi>Chriſt</hi> withdrew to avoid that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral death, which could not befall him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his own conſent, nor before the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time of his death was come.</p>
            <p>To oppoſe his Examples, I argued thus</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:41495:27"/>
            <p>If true Believers can fall away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then ſome have: But ſome have not: <hi>Ergo,</hi> they cannot. [Which in his Notes additional he calls a falſe Syllogiſm, but tells not why: But the Form, I ſuppoſe, ſeems ſtrange to him, proceeding <hi>a remotione conſequentis ad remotionem antecedentis.</hi> Yet the Scripture hath the like, which he, pretending to be a Teacher, ſhould not be ignorant of, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. <hi>ult.</hi> If Righteouſneſs were by the Law, <hi>Chriſt</hi> died in vain; to fill up the Syllogiſm, I muſt aſſume, But <hi>Chriſt</hi> died not in vain, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>Ergo</hi> Righteouſneſs is not by the Law.] Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> denied my <hi>major, Sequel</hi> he ſhould have ſaid, and in his Book brings in theſe words as my proof of it, <hi>Whatever is potenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, hath been done;</hi> which were none of mine, but his own. All that I ſaid was, That the Argument was good on his grounds; for in regard of the Activity of the cauſes of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, it cannot be imagined but ſome muſt fall away, if the thing were poſſible, and man left to his own ſtock of power; here I ſaid it was not abſurd to argue <hi>a poſſe ad eſſe,</hi> which, bold man! he hath adventured to tranſlate thus, <hi>Whatever is potential, hath been done.</hi> After a great deal of brangle, I urged againſt his firſt Example 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20. They that were Dogs and Swine, when they had eſcaped the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41495:28"/>pollutions of the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were not true Believers; and ſo their falling away, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of true Believers falling away totally and finally from Grace: But theſe perſons were Dogs and Swine, <hi>&amp;c. Ergo,</hi> not true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers. The <hi>major</hi> is evident: The <hi>minor</hi> we have <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>ult.</hi> compared. I offered alſo to prove againſt the Deſcription, but he broke me off. What I would have ſaid, was this; <hi>Judas</hi> was not a true Believer; <hi>Judas</hi> eſcaped the pollutions of the World through the knowledge of <hi>Chriſt: Ergo,</hi> Some that eſcape the pollutions of the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not true Believers. The <hi>major</hi> is evident by <hi>John</hi> 6. <hi>ult.</hi> The <hi>minor</hi> appears, becauſe the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, who knew his Converſation by familiar ſociety, ſaw no cauſe to ſuſpect him to be the Traytor, more than any other of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.21, 22. and therefore he was not viſibly wicked.</p>
            <p>Againſt his other Inſtance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.5, 6. I would have urged, That if thoſe who were in the judgement of Charity true Believers, are ſuppoſed, to the making of them ſuch, to have better things then thoſe that fell away; then thoſe that fell away were not true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers: But the Antecedent is true; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Conſequent. The Antecedent is proved by <hi>ver.</hi> 9. If the <hi>Arminians</hi> think to get off, by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41495:28"/>pretending that the things aſcribed to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are ſaid to be better, not in nature, but event; <hi>ver.</hi> 9. will afford a confutation <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>things that have ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them,</hi> i. e. <hi>no more ſeparable from Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then Salvation from it ſelf.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 10. ſuggeſts another, Thoſe things which God ſhould be unrighteous in not rewarding, were better than thoſe, which God ſhould not be unrighteous in not rewarding: But the things aſcribed to true Believers were ſuch as God ſhould be unrighteous in not reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Ergo,</hi> they were better then thoſe which God ſhould not be unrighteous in not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding, <hi>viz.</hi> the things aſcribed to them that fell away, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6.</p>
            <p>After a long rambling Diſcourſe, I urged to Mr. <hi>Ives,</hi> That if ſome true Believers might fall away totally and finally from Grace, then all might: But all could not (according to his own grant): <hi>Ergo,</hi> not ſome. I proved the Conſequence, becauſe <hi>Paribus paria conveniunt.</hi> He denied that though there be the like reaſon for the falling away of all, that there is for ſome, that therefore it followed, That if ſome might, then all might. Which being ſo groſly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, I appealed to the Judgment of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Hearers, and ſo left it. I called
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41495:29"/>upon him to hear <hi>Chriſts</hi> own Argument <hi>à pari,</hi> from <hi>David</hi>'s eating of the Shewbread, lawful onely ordinarily to the Prieſts; to the Diſciples plucking of the Ears of Corn on the Sabbath, for the ſupply of a preſent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.3, 4. But being an enemy to vain janglings, I deſiſted, as I did often, to proſecute ſomething elſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the firſt main Argument from 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. They that cannot ſin, as wicked men do, cannot fail away totally and finally from Grace: But true Believers cannot ſin as wicked men do: <hi>Ergo,</hi> true Believers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fall away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> asked what I meant by <hi>cannot ſin.</hi> I anſwered, Not as to the <hi>acts of ſin,</hi> but the <hi>manner</hi> [which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> leaves out, and makes my Anſwer non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe] of ſinning. After many ſuperfluous words, he ſaid, That if by <hi>cannot</hi> I meant, neither for the preſent, nor future; fall from that ſtate, and ſin as the wicked do, then he denied my <hi>minor.</hi> [Mr. <hi>Ives</hi>'s additional Notes about the acception of the word <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, p.</hi> 100. are rendred inſignificant by the proof of my <hi>minor,</hi> and therefore I omit them.] To prove my <hi>minor,</hi> I quoted 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God cannot commit ſin, &amp;c.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> preſently replied, That this proved <hi>no body could ſin at all.</hi> I anſwered,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41495:29"/>That either was meant, that they could not ſin at all, or not as wicked men do. Not the former; for proof I quoted <hi>chap.</hi> 1.8.10. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the latter; for I knew no <hi>tertium.</hi> And ſo I formed my Argument thus: Whoſoever is born of God cannot ſin as wicked men do: But all true Believers are born of God: <hi>Ergo,</hi> true Believers cannot ſin as wicked men do. [Which Argument Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> hath omitted.] Yet he continued his Cavil, That if the <hi>not ſinning</hi> was meant not at preſent, nor future, he denied it. And I proved it thus: The reaſon here aſſigned of the Believers, or born of God, their not ſinning as wicked men do, is of equal force to exclude his future, as his preſent not ſinning as wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men do, <hi>viz. becauſe the ſeed of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in him, ver.</hi> 9. Whence I argued thus, They in whom the ſeed of God remains, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſin as wicked men do: But in thoſe who are born of God, the ſeed of God remains; <hi>Ergo,</hi> Whoſoever is born of God cannot ſin as wicked men do. Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> cavilled much about the term <hi>remain,</hi> which I urged as plainly excluding a <hi>ceaſing</hi> or loſing of Grace totally: And he pretended that my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was but like this, <hi>They that come into this Houſe, remain in it:</hi> Ergo, <hi>They cannot ceaſe from remaining in it.</hi> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41495:30"/>That it was <hi>fallacia compoſitionis</hi> and <hi>diviſionis,</hi> (as we ſay in Logick) to ſay Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, whilſt Believers, cannot ceaſe to be Believers; for they cannot be both as to ſtate at the ſame time: But the Queſtion is, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they that are ſuch, may become Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers? And as to his Inſtance, if applied to our Queſtion, the meaning is not, Whether he that is now in the Houſe, may be out of it at the ſame time? but, Whether he that is in it, can afterwards go out? which by force, or other impediment, may become to him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, though poſſible in it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Here he cavilling about the word <hi>ſeed of God,</hi> I asked him how he underſtood the Phraſe, becauſe I thought it ſo plain, as that I ſuppoſed he took it in the ſame ſenſe I did, and as 'twas commonly underſtood, <hi>viz.</hi> for a <hi>Principle of Grace:</hi> Which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not; but at length he ſaid, he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by it <hi>the Word of God,</hi> and quoted 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23, 24. To which I replied, That in that place the Word is not called the <hi>Seed of God,</hi> but Believers are ſaid to be <hi>born of incorruptible Seed by the Word.</hi> But ſuppoſe it had, yet the ſenſe is the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> That the impreſſions of the Word remain in a true Believer; in which ſenſe 'tis ſaid, <hi>The Word abides for ever,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23, 25. At laſt I proved, That the Seed of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41495:30"/>God cannot but remain in a true Believer, from the <hi>Promiſe:</hi> Thoſe to whom God hath made a Promiſe, that in them the Seed [or Principle of Grace] ſhall remain, in them it cannot but remain: But to all true Believers God hath made ſuch a Promiſe: <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Seed cannot but remain in them. He deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>major,</hi> I proved it thus: If the Seed of God remain not in them to whom God hath promiſed, then the Promiſes of God are untrue: But they are not untrue: <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Seed of God ſhall remain, <hi>&amp;c. [Note,</hi> That here it was that Mr. <hi>Lueff</hi> admoniſhed Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> of his ignorance in the terms of Art, he denying the <hi>major,</hi> when he ſhould have ſaid the <hi>Sequel</hi> or <hi>Conſequence;</hi> and not in the former Syllogiſm, which was <hi>Categorical,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> ſuggeſts, <hi>pag.</hi> 118. of his Book, like himſelf, <hi>i. e.</hi> a man that makes no conſcience of lying, to ſlur his Adverſary.] Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> gave inſtance in the Promiſe of God to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> That the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> ſhould be to his ſeed an everlaſting Poſſeſſion, and yet that he would ſcatter them among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which Promiſe he pretended had no Condition, either where it is found, or elſewhere in Scripture; though he boldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies his Aſſertion, <hi>pag.</hi> 120.</p>
            <p>I offered to prove that that Promiſe was
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41495:31"/>true, notwithſtanding the non-performance of it, as it might ſeem: but was hindred by his Clamors. I ſhall give an account of what I would have ſaid, and began to ſpeak for inſtance, wherein a godly man cannot ſin as the wicked do; but could not be heard for the rudeneſs of my Antagoniſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>the courſe of ſin is interrupted by ſincere repentance</hi> in a godly man: So much is the oppoſition of the righteous man to the wicked, who imitates the Devil in ſinning from the beginning, <hi>ver.</hi> 8, 9. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports: For ſimply, as to the continuing to do evil, the oppoſition between them cannot lie: The wicked man cannot get his heart to repent ſincerely of his ſins, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.21. and <hi>chap.</hi> 16.11. Something like it, but not the ſame, was found in <hi>Ahab, Nineveh, Judas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The godly man ſins not with <hi>full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of will;</hi> ſo much thoſe Metaphors imply <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. compared with 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.25. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of himſelf whilſt a Believer, affirms, that he was <hi>carnal</hi> indeed, but not ſimply; for he adds, <hi>ſold under ſin, i. e.</hi> an involuntary Captive, as he ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains his meaning, when he tells us, <hi>For that which I do, I allow not, ver.</hi> 15. [See other like Phraſes to the end of the Chapter.] But of <hi>Ahab</hi> the Holy Ghoſt affirms, That
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41495:31"/>
               <hi>be ſold himſelf to work wickedneſs.</hi> If it be objected, that the Text ſays, <hi>There was none like to Ahab;</hi> I anſwer, For degree, not for kind of wickedneſs, muſt we underſtand that Negative. That there is in a godly man but a partial conſent of Will, appears by <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. where the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>The ſpirit luſts againſt the fleſh;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>concupiſcit;</hi> it notes an ardent deſire <hi>(viz.)</hi> of victory in the new Nature over the old, ſuch as to be found in enemies, (ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports): Or elſe it may allude to Contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in Nature, of which we obſerve in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, that they endeavour <hi>mutuo ſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellere,</hi> to drive out one another, when they meet in the ſame ſubject.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another difference between the godly and wicked mans ſinning, lies in this, That the <hi>former hath not a ſetled purpoſe to ſin; but the latter hath. Peter,</hi> whoſe ſin the enemies of the Saints Perſeverance do ſo tragically ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate, was ſo far from reſolving to deny his Maſter, that he reſolved againſt it with much vehemency, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.39. Whereas <hi>Judas</hi> kept fixed, notwithſtanding the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful threatning uttered againſt him, in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to betray him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.27. compar'd with <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.24. But more of this after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, when we anſwer the Inſtances of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Peter, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:41495:32"/>
            <p>I now proceed to the ſecond Argument, from <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. Whatever God hath promiſed, ſhall certainly be accompliſhed: But God hath promiſed that Believers ſhall not fall away totally and finally from Grace: <hi>Ergo,</hi> This Promiſe ſhall certainly be accompliſhed. Here I ſhall firſt take notice of, and anſwer what the <hi>Arminians</hi> urge againſt the <hi>major;</hi> which will alſo anſwer with advantage Mr. <hi>Ives</hi>'s Inſtance of the Promiſe of the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> which I touched at then, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That it being conditional, noted but a connexion between the Benefit and their Obedience, (though Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> omits it).</p>
            <p>The <hi>major</hi> they deny, upon pretence of Inſtances of ſome Promiſes not fulfilled.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, 1. That the Inſtances which they bring, <hi>viz. Numb.</hi> 14.18. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. do not import a Promiſe to every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual perſon, <hi>qua talis,</hi> as ſuch, that they ſhould enter into <hi>Canaan,</hi> or ſucceed their Parents in the Office of the Prieſthood; but it was fulfilled, in that the Stock of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did enter, and of <hi>Levi</hi> tranſmitted the Office to their Children, though particular Perſons were cut off, and debarred that Privilege.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſe the Promiſes were made to individual Perſons, and conditionally; yet
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41495:32"/>cannot be affirmed, that the Promiſes were broken; <hi>Non enim affirmat connexa vel condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionata promiſſio, conſequentem partem illius axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omatis fore, ſed connexionem tantùm conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis parte cum antecedente, quam ſemper etiam Deus praeſtat,</hi> as <hi>Ames</hi> well obſerves in <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Art.</hi> 5. <hi>de Perſeverantia, cap.</hi> 2. The ſum is, Conditional Promiſes engage but for a connexion of Duty and Benefit. As when God ſays, <hi>Ye ſhall keep my Statutes, and my Judgments; which if a man do, he ſhall live in them, Lev.</hi> 18.5. he does not ſtrictly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that a man ſhall live by keeping his Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and Judgments; but that there ſhall be a certain connexion between perfect Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Life thereby, which is certainly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, though no man lives by ſuch Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, (innate corruption diſabling him thereto, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.)</p>
            <p>To the <hi>minor,</hi> That God hath made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Perſeverance to true Believers, which we prove by <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>John</hi> 10.28. the general Anſwer is, That theſe Promiſes are <hi>conditional.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> would aſſign none, though much urged, nor would be perſwaded that he was bound by the Law of Diſpute ſo to do.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> and others give this, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That <hi>Man does his Duty.</hi> To which I
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41495:33"/>anſwer, That this is the very <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>ſubject</hi> of the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and therefore cannot be the <hi>Condition</hi> of it. All the Promiſes we produce do import an Obligation laid by God on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to enable us to our Duty, ſo far as is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the prevention of a total and final falling away from Grace.]</p>
            <p>Againſt the firſt Promiſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. the <hi>Arminians</hi> make divers Exceptions, which I ſhall firſt anſwer, and then repeat Mr. <hi>Ives</hi>'s.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That 'tis a Conditional Promiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Foedus, a Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This word is often taken for a ſimple Promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.19. and <hi>chap.</hi> 9.9. 2. The Apoſtle mentioning this Promiſe calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. which is rendred <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> or <hi>Will, chap.</hi> 9.17. 3. Though the Benefits of the Covenant of Grace, compar'd one with another, have the nature of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as Faith of Juſtification; yet that hinders not but that the whole, and each part, are conveyed as Legacies, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.38. the Promiſe is, That we ſhall be Gods People.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others bear us in hand, it was made to the whole People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and not only to true Believers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. A Promiſe of Continuance with God, does ſuppoſe a Being with him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Promiſe is made to them all, in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41495:33"/>reſpect of their Covenant, State, and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of true Faith: but yet it was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to any but true Believers; for they are the Children of the Promiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8. and for their comfort it was intended.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to the matter of it,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They object, That the words may as well be conſtrued a Promiſe to keep Believers from falling away from any Degree of Grace, as totally and finally.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The very Event gives ground not to make that interpretation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.46.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is not ſaid to depart, properly, who does not wholly relinquiſh or forſake whom he was with.</p>
            <p>Now to Mr. <hi>Ives</hi>'s Anſwer, which was by denial,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it was any Promiſe, either abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely or conditionally to all true Believers. Whereupon I argued thus: Either this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. is made to all true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or onely to ſome, or to Unbelievers: But neither is it made to ſome onely, nor to Unbelievers: <hi>Ergo,</hi> To all true Believers. I proved that it was not made, as he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to ſome onely. Spiritual Promiſes made to the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, are made to all true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers: But ſuch is this: <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is made to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41495:34"/>all true Believers. I proved my <hi>major,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God contains all true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, according to <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. I proved further, that this Promiſe <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. belonged to all true Believers, from a Promiſe of the New Teſtament of the ſame import, <hi>(viz.)</hi> a Promiſe of Perſeverance, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.28. Whence I argued, That if this Promiſe belonged to all true Believers, then ſo did that, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. But this did: <hi>Ergo,</hi> That. [As for what he urges of Mr. <hi>Fowlers,</hi> as aiding me, though I acknowledge his worth much beyond mine, yet I will appeal to Mr. <hi>Fewler,</hi> and any of the ſober Hearers, whether Mr. <hi>Fowler</hi> did not often tell Mr. <hi>Ives, I do but repeat what Mr. Danſon ſaid:</hi> And Mr. <hi>Ives</hi>'s diſingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity is remarkable, that he leaves out the word <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> which I did often, perhaps not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, add, as a limitation of the Promiſes made to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which, under them, as Types, agreed to the Believers of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And where he brings in the ſame Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument in other words, as a new Argument, he abuſes me; for all that were ingenuous of the Auditors will bear me witneſs, that by the many breaks (through his impertinent Harangues, which he hath had ſo much wit as to leave out) in the Diſcourſe, I was fain to repeat the ſame Argument over and over,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41495:34"/>to gain an Anſwer.] I urged alſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. which evidently proves, that the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.38. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. agrees to others than them, <hi>(viz.)</hi> all true Believers. And let any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Perſon read his own report of his Anſwer, and they ſhall find it meer words, and that he does himſelf as little ſervice to evade the Argument, as a Mouſe in a Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barrel, with all her ſtrugling to get out. I urged further, That if the whole Covenant of Grace made with <hi>Iſrael, Jer.</hi> 32.38. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to all Believers, then part of it <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Promiſe of Perſeverance, <hi>ver.</hi> 40. But the whole does: <hi>Ergo,</hi> That part. The <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> (which he ſtill ignorantly called the <hi>Major</hi>) I proved, becauſe that Branch of it was contained under the whole, as a Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular under an Univerſal. And whereas he brings me in ſaying, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. is part of the Covenant of Grace, and therefore the whole; that's falſe: and Mr. <hi>Fowler</hi>'s inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure (though he baſely conceals what he ſaid) was to reprove him for an undue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating of my words, which were (as Mr. <hi>Fowler</hi> told him) That <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. being part of the Covenant of Grace, belongs to all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, under the title of the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, becauſe the whole does.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:41495:35"/>
            <p n="2">2. As Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> denied the Promiſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. was made to all Believers; ſo he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that it was a Promiſe of Perſeverance at all, but that they may be read, <hi>But let them not depart from me;</hi> and for this quotes <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> whom he named not in the Conference, and ſubjoyns, <hi>ver.</hi> 39. <hi>that they may fear me.</hi> To which I anſwer him, that the words, <hi>(viz.)</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are rendred, and ſo owned by the Remonſtrants and others, <hi>That they may not depart, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t non recedant.</hi> As for <hi>Calvin,</hi> he manifeſts his impudence to the height, in fathering ſuch an Interpretation on him: Let any one that underſtands <hi>Latin,</hi> read his Comment on <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. and believe their own eyes. <hi>Calvin</hi> does not ſo much as mention any ſuch Tranſlation of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> words, but onely what our Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on follows. As for <hi>ver.</hi> 39. that makes againſt Mr. <hi>Ives;</hi> for the ſence is the very ſame with <hi>ver.</hi> 40. <hi>(viz.)</hi> a Promiſe of Perſeverance i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Fear of God. [This ſecond Branch o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mr. <hi>Ives</hi>'s Anſwer was brought in by ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> impertinent words of his, in the midſt of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Diſcourſe about the <hi>Perſons</hi> to whom the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was made, ſuppoſing it ſuch: but ſo order ſake I have tranſpoſed it hither. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 133.] The ſecond Promiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Perſeverance I alledged, was, <hi>John</hi> 10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:41495:35"/>whence I argued thus; They that cannot be plucked out of Chriſt's hand, cannot fall away totally and finally from Grace: True Believers cannot be plucked out of Chriſt's hand: <hi>Ergo,</hi> True Believers cannot fall away totally, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> anſwers, That I concluded not the Queſtion, becauſe I argued <hi>indefinitely,</hi> not <hi>univerſally,</hi> [which Terms he uſed not then, ſo far as Memory and Notes inform me:] But how ſimple this Anſwer is, let any judge; for he firſt, for his advantage, ſtated the Queſtion <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, (viz.)</hi> That ſome true Believers [not all] may fall away. Again, he oppoſes <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite</hi> to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal;</hi> whereas an <hi>Indefinite</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition may be either <hi>Particular</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal,</hi> as <hi>the matter is contingent or neceſſary.</hi> And he repeated my words in an Hypothetical form; If none of the Sheep of Chriſt can be plucked out of Chriſts hand, then no true Believer can fall away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo denied the <hi>Major,</hi> the <hi>Conſequence</hi> he ſhould have ſaid, and being friendly admoniſhed of his error, pretended they were all one: However, I told him the Conſequence was evident, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all true Believers are Chriſts Sheep; which by his frequent diverſions I was fain to repeat, and he would outface me then, as now in his Book, that I intended each Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41495:36"/>for a new <hi>Medium,</hi> and ſo argued <hi>idem per idem;</hi> whereas I ſtuck to that Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, till I had a plain and direct Anſwer. At laſt he ſaid, That <hi>Metaphors</hi> prove nothing. I told him, Yes, they did in that Similitude upon which they are grounded; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon appealed to Mr. <hi>Fowler,</hi> as Moderator, whom at firſt I propoſed to Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> for that Office, if he would pleaſe to undertake it: which was the reaſon of his ſo frequent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſure, that he might ſhew Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> when I proved directly, and he anſwered not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly. At laſt he told us, That the Promiſe referred to the day of Judgment; That when Chriſts Sheep are poſſeſſed of Eternal Life, they ſhall not be plucked out of his hand, or periſh: Which was ſo abſurd an Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That Mr. <hi>Fowler</hi> asked him ſolemnly, Whether he himſelf did believe it? To which the ſum of his Anſwer was, That it was no abſurdity. Here he quoted <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> as holding that ſome true Believers may fall away. Mr. <hi>Fowler</hi>'s Anſwer I ſhall refer to the Appendix. When Mr. <hi>Fowler</hi> and he had done, I repeated my former Argument, and Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> denied that that Phraſe of <hi>Chriſts Sheep</hi> included <hi>all true Believers;</hi> which I proved from the deſcription. <hi>ver.</hi> 27. that they <hi>hear Chriſts voice, and know him, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41495:36"/>him.</hi> Then I proceeded from <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. If true Believers be every where in Scripture ſet forth by Similitudes that note ſtability and firmneſs, then they cannot fall away from Grace totally and finally: <hi>Sed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum prius: Ergo, &amp; poſterius.</hi> Here he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the <hi>major</hi> again; he was ſo dull, he could not think of a <hi>Conſequence,</hi> though of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten told; and would not be perſwaded to anſwer, becauſe it was a Parable: To which I replied, That even Parables do afford <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums</hi> from their general ſcope; and the ground of the Metaphor in <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.24. was evident, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That a true Believer is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to an Houſe built on a Rock, becauſe they agree <hi>in uno tertio</hi> ſtability and firmneſs, notwithſtanding aſſaults that might endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger their fall. But he continuing obſtinate, I told him he was a conceited ignorant <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> not <hi>Fellow,</hi> (as he quotes my words, both there, and twice beſides.) Upon my calling him ſo, he produced a Book of mine, which I was neceſſitated by their miſreports to publiſh againſt the Quakers, wherein <hi>I accuſed Chriſt of ignorance,</hi> as he pretneded: Whereas I did not accuſe him; for Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuppoſes a Fault, whereas Chriſts Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of many things was not ſuch; as not
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41495:37"/>his ignorance of the day of Judgment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.36. What I ſaid, was, that it was not evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from Scripture, that Chriſt did, as Man, know <hi>Judas</hi> to be a Devil from the <hi>firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of his choice of him. What I accuſed Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> of diſingenuity in, was his not read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the laſt Clauſe of the Paragraph in my Book, concerning Chriſts ignorance; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſay, Whether that [foregoing Aſſertion] be true or falſe, yet Chriſt might deal with <hi>Judas</hi> according to what he was viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; Yet hath Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> the front to affirm, That the Perſon he employed read word for word; whereas all took notice, that he ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him at the laſt Clauſe, which therefore, when I had the Book, I read my ſelf. I alſo accuſed Mr. <hi>Ives,</hi> I confeſs, for diſturbing us with impertinencies; for what was my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake in that Aſſertion, to the Saints Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. Whatſoever our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath prayed for, ſhall certainly come to paſs: But he hath prayed for the Saints Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or that they may not fall away totally and finally from Grace: <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Saints ſhall perſevere.</p>
            <p>The <hi>major</hi> I proved by <hi>John</hi> 11.42. <hi>And I knew</hi> (ſays Chriſt to the Father) <hi>that thou heareſt me always:</hi> To which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41495:37"/>no anſwer, but denied the <hi>major,</hi> and inſtanced in Chriſts Prayer, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.34. which he pretended was not anſwered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all Chriſts Enemies that put him to death were not forgiven. To which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, 1. That it was anſwered in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of 3000 of them, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.23, 41. and that the term <hi>them</hi> is taken indefinitely. To which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> replied, That <hi>an Indefinite is equivalent to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal:</hi> But I rejoyned to him, That it is not alway ſo, but onely ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, <hi>(viz.) in materia neceſſaria, non contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genti;</hi> which I would have explained to him, but that his rude clamor would not give me leave: but I ſhall now do it, for the help of the unlearned. In Logick we call that an Indefinite Propoſition or Enunciation, which hath no Note of Quantity Univerſal or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſet before it, but yet muſt ever be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood either Univerſally, or Particularly; as, <hi>Man is a reaſonable Creature; Mothers love their Children.</hi> In the former Inſtance, we underſtand <hi>every Man:</hi> In the latter, <hi>ſome Mothers.</hi> In the former Inſtance, we call the Predicate, or that which is affirmed of Man, <hi>(viz.) a reaſonable Creature, materia neceſſaria,</hi> or that which agrees to Man <hi>neceſſarily;</hi> for we cannot conceive a Man not to be a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Creature, without a contradiction. In
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41495:38"/>the latter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſtance, we call the Predicate, or that which is affirmed of Mothers, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That they <hi>love their Children, materia contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens,</hi> that is, that which may be, or not be, in Mothers; for one Branch of natural Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, is to be <hi>without natural affection,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Original, <hi>expertes charitatis naturalis, Scultetus in loc.</hi> that is, without thoſe affections which by inſtinct of Nature we bear to thoſe that in Nature and Blood are conjoyned to us, ſuch as are thoſe between Parents and Children. To apply all this now to the Text before us, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.34. compared with <hi>John</hi> 17.24. where Chriſt ſpeaking of the Elect, prays <hi>indefinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Father, I will that they alſo whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my Glory, &amp;c.</hi> In the former place, Chriſt prays but for <hi>ſome</hi> of his Perſecuters: In the latter place he prays for <hi>all</hi> that the Father had given him; though <hi>ſome</hi> is not expreſſed in the one place, nor <hi>all</hi> in the other: Becauſe the Election of God made the Salvation of <hi>all</hi> thoſe that were given to Chriſt <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and but onely <hi>of ſome of his Perſecuters, (viz.)</hi> thoſe that were given him by the Father.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I anſwered to Mr. <hi>Ives,</hi> That this Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſts, though made <hi>as a private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:41495:38"/>and not as <hi>Mediator,</hi> by vertue of that Law of Love which requires us to pray for them that deſpitefully uſe us, and perſecute us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.44. which Law he was under, by being <hi>made under the Law, Gal.</hi> 4.4. was yet <hi>anſwered, as truly,</hi> as thoſe Prayers which he made as Mediator, ſuppoſing (but not granting) that he prayed for all; becauſe, if he did, there was then ſuch a Condition, in reſpect of the diſpoſition of the Party pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, implied, as to the forgiveneſs of all his Perſecuters, as was expreſſed, when he prayed for his own natural life, <hi>(viz.) Nevertheleſs, not my will, but thy will be done, Luke</hi> 22.42. [Where note Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> miſrepreſenting of my words, as if I acknowledged that ſome of Chriſts Prayers were not anſwered.] Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> demanded of me, Where that diſtinction between Chriſts praying as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſon, and as a Mediator, was found? I replied in <hi>John</hi> 17.24. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.39. compar'd together; which I would have made out, but that he drown'd mine, with his Stentorian Voice, and, <hi>Pilate</hi>-like, asked a Queſtion which he would not take an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to, <hi>John</hi> 18.38. I ſhall ſay onely thus much now, that <hi>in the one</hi> he prayed for thoſe that were given to him; <hi>in the other place,</hi> for the prevention of his own death,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41495:39"/>the grant whereof, would have rendred him uncapable of being our Mediator.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I now reply, (what I had then for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in my thoughts, when I diſcourſed with Mr. <hi>Ives,</hi> but prevented in ſpeaking it, &amp; many other things, by his uncivil demeanour) That in ſtrictneſs of ſpeech <hi>there is no Prayer but what is abſolute;</hi> which I ground upon the nature of Prayer, <hi>(viz.)</hi> a ſubmiſs repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Will before God, to the end it may be performed by him. The repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Velleity,</hi> whereby we would will a thing, if ſomething did not hinder, is not Prayer, properly ſo called. The words are <hi>Ames</hi>'s, tranſlated out of his <hi>Coronis, Art.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. which yet was the Judgment of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius</hi> himſelf, as the ſaid Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> there aſſures us upon the report of credible Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who heard <hi>Arminius</hi> in his publick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputations deliver himſelf to that effect. I find alſo the ſame Aſſertion in <hi>Becanus Sum. Theol. Tom.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>queſt.</hi> 3. where, among other Reaſons, he gives this, which is popular and plain; <hi>Nam noſtra oratio debet eſse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncta cum certa ſpe ſeu fiducia conſequendi id quod petimus, Jac.</hi> 1.6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> i. e. For our Prayer ought to be joyned with a certain hope or aſſurance of obtaining that which we pray for, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.6. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.22. But
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41495:39"/>when we propound or manifeſt a bare, uneffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual deſire, we do it not with a certain confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of obtaining what is deſired, but rather with aſſurance of the contrary; as if a Man ſhould pray, Oh that God would let me live over again my time that is paſt. Thus far <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus.</hi> But I muſt confeſs, the firſt that I met this Notion in, was Mr. <hi>Richard Hooker,</hi> a very learned Perſon, <hi>Eccleſiaſt. Polity, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>m.</hi> 48. where he ſays, Of Prayer there are two uſes: It ſerveth as a mean to procure thoſe things which God hath promiſed to grant when we ask; and it ſerveth as a mean to expreſs our lawful deſires alſo towards that, which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſhall have, or no, we know not, till we ſee the event. Onely Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſeems to differ from the Learned Men above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, in that he makes it an over-reſtrained conſideration of Prayer, to tye it onely to this uſe, to be a choſen mean, whereby the Will reſolveth to ſeek that, which the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding certainly knoweth it ſhall obtain. I have inſiſted the longer on this, becauſe it may many ways be uſeful to us, and fully anſwers the <hi>Arminians</hi> cavil about Chriſts not being anſwered in ſome of his Prayers. For if we hold, that no repreſentation of our deſire to God, of what we do not abſolutely peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for, is ſtrictly a Prayer; then our <hi>major</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:41495:40"/>Propoſition, Whatever Chriſt prayed for, he was heard in, is true, without limitation; and Mr. <hi>Ives,</hi> and other <hi>Arminians, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants, &amp;c.</hi> inſtance inſufficient. If we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that ſuch a repreſentation of our deſires to God, may be called <hi>Prayer;</hi> yet our <hi>major</hi> is true, according to the more common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the <hi>term</hi> Prayer, and our uſe of it in the Aſſumption or <hi>minor, (viz.)</hi> for ſuch a repreſentation of Chriſts deſire to God in general, and of Perſeverance in particular, as ſerved for a means to procure what God had promiſed to grant him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another Inſtance which the Remonſtrants give of Chriſts Prayer not anſwered, is</hi> Joh. 17.25, 21. <hi>where he prays, That they may be kept from evil, and be one among themſelves; yet do they ſin, and diſagree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Ames,</hi> that <hi>Remonſtrantium malleus,</hi> puts an Anſwer in my mouth: Chriſt does not pray for their immediate deliverance from all evil, nor ſo from diſcord; but for a gradual deliverance, as <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12, 13. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports.</p>
            <p>The <hi>minor,</hi> that Chriſt prayed for the Saints Perſeverance, we prove by two Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>John</hi> 17.15, 20. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32.</p>
            <p>To this the <hi>Arminians</hi> ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That John</hi> 17.15. <hi>may be meant of the Diſciples onely.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:41495:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The 20th <hi>verſe</hi> takes of that Gloſs, <hi>Neither pray I for theſe alone, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That by evil,</hi> verſe 15. <hi>may be meant only Perſecutions, and particularly thoſe that did attend Chriſts apprehenſion and death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Suppoſing what they affirm, yet thoſe Perſecutions were conſidered as <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations to Apoſtacy;</hi> and therefore all other Temptations muſt be included, which might endanger their fall <hi>ex natura rei.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 12. intimates, that he had hitherto kept them from that evil by which <hi>Judas</hi> fell, which was not Perſecution, but Covetouſneſs.</p>
            <p>To that other place of Scripture, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32. the <hi>Arminians</hi> ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That this might be a ſpecial Privilege of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Then hereby we gain a Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of what overthrows their grand Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the poſſibility of any true Believers total and final Apoſtacy. 1. That the praedeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination or Decree abſolute of perſeverance, deprives the Will of its native liberty. 2. That Admonitions to avoid a Danger in any reſpect impoſſible, are vain and uſeleſs; for after this Prayer, Chriſt ſays to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Ariſe, and pray, that ye enter not into temptation, Luke</hi> 22.46. 3. That a true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever falls away at leaſt totally from Grace,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41495:41"/>when he falls into heynous ſins (ſuch as we readily acknowledge <hi>Peters</hi> denying his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to have been.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. But we deny that this Promiſe was to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, <hi>verſe</hi> 31. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ye,</hi> in the plural Number, <hi>ver.</hi> 28, 29. Chriſt promiſes them a Kingdom for continuing with him in his Temptations, which muſt look forward, as well as backward; for, <hi>He that endures to the end ſhall be ſaved, Mat.</hi> 24.13. nor yet to the Apoſtles onely (as we ſawbefore, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.15, 20.)</p>
            <p>To thoſe four Arguments diſcuſſed, I ſhall add two more, which we had not time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. Whatever neceſſary to their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation the Saints pray for, they ſhall obtain: But the Saints pray for perſeverance, and it is neceſſary to their Salvation: <hi>Ergo,</hi> They ſhall obtain it. The <hi>major</hi> is evident by <hi>John</hi> 16.13. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.14. The <hi>minor,</hi> by <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Deliver us from evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the <hi>minor</hi> the <hi>Arminians</hi> object, <hi>That in that place the Saints pray, that they may not be lead into temptation at all; and yet are not heard in that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If the <hi>total exemption from ſin</hi> be a Mercy the Saints have no warrant by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to expect in this life, then the Saints
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41495:41"/>Prayer for that, is not <hi>Prayer</hi> [ſtrictly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led] (as I ſhewed before) but a repreſentation of their deſire of a thing in it ſelf deſirable: And look what Anſwer may be made about <hi>Chriſts</hi> not being heard, when he prayed that <hi>the Cup might paſs from him, Matth.</hi> 26.39. the ſame will ſuffice <hi>(mutatis mutandis)</hi> to invalidate the <hi>Arminians</hi> pretence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. This Exception oppoſes not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Propoſitions, in which there is a <hi>limitation</hi> of that Prayer of the Saints that ſhall always be <hi>heard, by giving the very thing prayed for, to that which is neceſſary to the Saints Salvation;</hi> which a not leading into temptation at all, is not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. None of the Elect can fall away totally and finally from Grace: But all true Believers are Elect: <hi>Ergo,</hi> No true Believers can fall away totally and finally from Grace.</p>
            <p>I prove the <hi>major</hi> and <hi>minor,</hi> firſt by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then by plain Scripture.</p>
            <p>The <hi>major</hi> is denied, becauſe the <hi>Arminians</hi> ſuppoſe the Decree of God concerning Mens Salvation (which we call <hi>Election</hi>) to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional; againſt which I argue thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. If Election be conditional, then it is uncertain: But it is not uncertain: <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> It is not conditional.</p>
            <p>I prove the Conſequence thus.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:41495:42"/>
            <p>That which depends on the Freedom of Mans Will, is uncertain: But conditional Election depends on the Freedom of Mans Will: Therefore it is uncertain.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Arminians</hi> deny the <hi>major,</hi> becauſe God did foreknow mens Faith. To which I reply, That upon their Hypotheſis, God did not, nor could foreknow the Perſons Faith whom he conditionally Elected; which I prove thus.</p>
            <p>That which was not future, God could not foreknow: But the Faith of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally Elected was not future: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Their Faith God could not foreknow.</p>
            <p>The <hi>minor</hi> is proved thus:</p>
            <p>What God did not will, was not future: But God did not will the Faith of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally elected: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Their Faith was not future. The <hi>minor</hi> is their own; for they hold the <hi>terminus ad quem praedeſtinationis</hi> to be only <hi>Glory,</hi> not Grace, <hi>i. e.</hi> That God wills Glory or Salvation to Believers, not Faith it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The <hi>major</hi> I prove thus:</p>
            <p>If that was future wich God did not will, then there was an Effect without a Cauſe: But the Conſequent is falſe: <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſo is the Antecedent.</p>
            <p>The Conſequence is evident, becauſe from
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41495:42"/>Eternity there was nothing to cauſe that which was poſſible, to become future, but the Will of God: <hi>Ergo,</hi> If any thing was future, which God did not will, 'twas an Effect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Cauſe. [And this is the inſoluble demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration that cuts the throat of <hi>Scientia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> whereupon the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and <hi>Arminians,</hi> and all thoſe that oppoſe the abſoluteneſs of Gods Decrees, do and muſt relie, unleſs they will turn Atheiſts, and with <hi>Cicero</hi> deny that God foreknows things to come, ſays the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Twiſſe</hi> againſt <hi>Cotton of Predeſtination, pag.</hi> 69. and hath irrefragably proved it in that large and elaborate Tract <hi>De Scientia media.</hi>]</p>
            <p>I argue againſt the conditional Decree which the <hi>Arminians</hi> extend even to thoſe that are in the event damned; though with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al they affirm, That he foreknows who will, and who will not perform that <hi>Condition, (viz.) Believing in Chriſt, and perſevering in that Belief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. That which imputes Folly to God, is not to be aſcribed to God: But ſo does a conditional Decree of ſaving thoſe whom God foreknows will not believe, and ſo will be damned: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Such a conditional Decree is not to be aſcribed to God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>minor</hi> is evident, becauſe a conditional
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41495:43"/>Decree makes God to reſolve to do that which for want of the performance of a Condition, which he knows will never be performed, he is reſolved not to do; <hi>(viz.)</hi> to ſave thoſe if they believe, whom he knows never will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and therefore for their unbelief is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to damn.</p>
            <p>Many things the <hi>Arminians</hi> urge for their conditional Decree of Election, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſeat is the Doctrine of Predeſtination. I will therefore onely take notice of one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> God hath elected Men to Salvation by Faith in Chriſt perſevered in: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Such Faith is the inſtrumental Cauſe or Condition of the Decree of Election.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We deny the <hi>Conſequence.</hi> The <hi>Conſequent</hi> ought to be, <hi>Ergo,</hi> Faith is the inſtrumental Cauſe of Salvation decreed. And that we acknowledge.</p>
            <p>We now proceed to the proof of the <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, All true Believers are Elect:</hi> For this the <hi>Arminians</hi> deny, and aſſert, That not Faith ſimply, but perſevered in, is the condition of Election. Againſt which Reaſon of theirs, I ſhall onely urge theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. If perſeverance in Faith be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition requiſite in the Object of Election, then no man whilſt he is living is the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41495:43"/>of Election [or an Elect perſon]: But ſome men whilſt they are living are Objects of Election, or Elect perſons: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in Faith is not a Condition requiſite in the Object of Election.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Conſequence</hi> is evident upon their own grounds, becauſe (ſay they) <hi>any one that is a true Believer may fall away;</hi> and 'tis onely <hi>he that endureth to the end ſhall be ſaved,</hi> our Lord tells us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.13.</p>
            <p>The <hi>minor</hi> is evident by 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.9. For <hi>God hath not appointed us to wrath, but to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Salvation by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 11.7. Believers are called <hi>the Election</hi> in the abſtract, which is more emphatical than to be barely called <hi>Elect,</hi> and intimates the cauſe of their preſent obtaining of Righteouſneſs, becauſe at preſent <hi>Elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the proof of my <hi>minor,</hi> I argue thus again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. If true Faith be a fruit of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then all true Believers are Elect: But the Antecedent is true: <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. I prove the Antecedent, firſt, by <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Having predeſtinated us to the Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of Children, &amp;c.</hi> compared with <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <hi>But as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the Sons of God, even to them that believe on his Name.</hi> Whence I argue
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41495:44"/>thus: He that hath predeſtinated to a State or Relation, hath predeſtinated to the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of that State or Relation: But God hath predeſtinated ſome to a State or Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>(viz) Adoption: Ergo,</hi> He hath predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated them alſo to the Foundation of that State or Relation, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to Faith.</p>
            <p>The <hi>major</hi> is evident, as otherwiſe, ſo by the inſtance of <hi>David,</hi> who being deſign'd to be <hi>Sauls</hi> Son-in Law, was alſo deſigned to marry his Daughter, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.21. for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch marriage, he could not ſtand in ſuch relation to <hi>Saul.</hi> Again, I prove it by that Appellation given to Faith, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. <hi>The Faith of Gods Elect.</hi> There can be no reaſon given hereof, but becauſe it is peculiar to the Elect: and why is it ſo? Becauſe either all that have true Faith are Gods Elect (which the <hi>Arminians</hi> deny), or elſe becauſe true Faith is a Fruit of Election, [whence that which they deny does evidently enough fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low] as <hi>Moulin</hi> obſerves, <hi>Anat. Armin. cap.</hi> 19. <hi>n.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>I now go on in the proof of my <hi>major,</hi> that none of the Elect can fall away totally and finally from true Grace, by Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Firſt Scripture is, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.24. <hi>For there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſigns and wonders, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41495:44"/>that (if it were poſſible) they ſhall deceive the very Elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which place many Exceptions are made.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>Perſons,</hi> That by <hi>Elect</hi> are not underſtood the Objects of Gods abſolute will or purpoſe of Salvation; but <hi>choice Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,</hi> or ſuch as <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>ſtrong in Faith, Rom.</hi> 4.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is not impoſſible that even they ſhould be deceived (according to the <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> own opinion.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſpecial proviſion God makes for the Elect, in ſhortning thoſe perillous days, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.22. ſhould rather be made for weak Believers, than ſtrong ones, becauſe the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer need it more.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the <hi>Phraſe, If it were poſſible,</hi> they except, That it notes onely a great difficulty, not a ſimple impoſſibility.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. We do not aſſert a ſimple impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, but <hi>ex hypotheſi,</hi> or upon ſuppoſition of Gods Decree and Promiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If by impoſſible, be meant only diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult; then by poſſible, is meant eaſie: But to interpret the Phraſe ſo here, is repugnant to the ſcope, which is to ſhew the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary diligence and ſucceſs of the Seducers, that, like the Devil, they would even ſet upon
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41495:45"/>Chriſt himſelf, and leave no ſtone unturned, no means unuſed, to accompliſh their deſign. If it were but a difficult thing, and not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, they would make new onſets, though frequently beaten off.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to the <hi>Event,</hi> they object, That it is ſeduction, not final and total, but partial, that the Letter of the Text imports.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The place it ſelf ſuggeſts groſs and damnable errors, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to look for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Meſſias</hi> than the true, <hi>ver.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It intimates the final deceiving of ſome, in oppoſition to the final perſeverance of others, <hi>ver.</hi> 11, 12, 13.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Arminians</hi> object, That the Elect could not be ſeduced by the Seducers; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could not fall away of themſelves, is a bad Conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Nor is that our Conſequence, but this, They that cannot be ſeduced by any means, cannot be ſeduced by falſe Prophets.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Conſequence is not abſurd, 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſeduction of falſe Teachers is moſt dangerous, called thererfore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the working of Satan,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9. <hi>vis efficax,</hi> an <hi>effectual working</hi> (as we may ſay) an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that cannot fail of ſucceſs, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſtrong deluſions, verſe</hi> 11. ſome render it <hi>efficacy of couſenage,</hi> that which will
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41495:45"/>impoſe upon the moſt ſagacious and wary perſon. And by that manner of ſeduction our firſt Parents fell, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. And by the like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>If any man offend not in word, the ſame is able alſo to bridle the whole body, James</hi> 3.2. we may ſay, He that can withſtand the attempts of Seducers, may be able to withſtand any other aſſault. 2. That Conſequence is not without another ground to ſupport it, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Becauſe he that falls away of himſelf, ſeduces himſelf; for he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to ſome falſhood under the ſhew of truth: Whatever therefore it is in him, that ſecures him from the danger of being ſeduced by others, will be alſo his ſecurity againſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction by himſelf.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Scripture to prove, That <hi>the Elect cannot fall away, &amp;c.</hi> is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.2. <hi>God hath not caſt away his People whom he foreknew:</hi> Where by <hi>foreknowing</hi> we muſt underſtand (according to the frequent uſage of the Phraſe in Scripture) <hi>a knowledge accompanied with affection;</hi> and we muſt obſerve, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle intimates a diſtinction between <hi>caſting away</hi> ſome of his People who <hi>were not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known,</hi> and the <hi>not caſting away</hi> thoſe that <hi>were;</hi> of whom he gives himſelf an Inſtance, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. This premiſed I argue thus. Thoſe whom God caſts not off, cannot fall away to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41495:46"/>and finally from Grace: But thoſe whom God foreknew, he caſts not off: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Thoſe whom God foreknows, [or the Elect] cannot fall away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>major</hi> is evident, becauſe God caſts off none but Unbelievers. The <hi>minor</hi> the Text affords.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Arminians</hi> anſwer to the <hi>minor,</hi> That though God caſts not off Men, they may caſt away themſelves, and ſo ceaſe to be Gods People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is fond; for if they did caſt off God, God muſt needs caſt off them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>To Mr. <hi>Ives</hi>'s Appendix.</head>
            <p>UPon review of what I have already done, I find a few words will ſuffice. They that would be ſatisfied as to the Judgment of the Fathers, about the Saints perſeverance, may find Paſſages enough for that end, collected to their hands, in Dr. <hi>Kendal</hi>'s <hi>Sancti Sanciti</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and in <hi>Latin</hi> in <hi>Hier. Zanch. de Perſ. Sanct. in Miſcell. V.</hi> 3. <hi>Oper.</hi> And as for <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,</hi> 'tis well known that he wrote a whole Book <hi>de Perſever. Sanct.</hi> and diſtinguiſhes
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41495:46"/>often between common and ſpecial Grace, as Mr. <hi>Fowler</hi> told Mr. <hi>Ives.</hi> And as for that worthy perſon Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> he does not determine againſt the Point, as we hold it, but ſays, <hi>From Matth.</hi> 13.6, 21. <hi>it may well be inferred, that thoſe ſhall not fall away in time of temptation, in whom the Word of God hath taken deep rooting. In the</hi> 11th <hi>of his</hi> 32 <hi>Directions, pag.</hi> 107.</p>
            <p>As for the Charge of <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> and the Paſſages he quotes out of Mr. <hi>Cottons Cov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Grace,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bridges,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> however in ſome Particulars they may ſound, I think the <hi>Reverend Mr. Caryl</hi> (whom Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> reflects upon for writing a Commendatory Epiſtle to <hi>Mr. Cotton's Tract</hi> abovementioned) ſpeaks the ſenſe of them all, in his excellent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon <hi>Job.</hi> 10.15. They put <hi>dangerous Suppoſitions</hi> oppoſite to theſe, who ſay, <hi>Let a godly man be never ſo wicked let him ſin as much as he will, yet it ſhall be well with him:</hi> [which is the language of ſuch as Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> whom Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> quotes, and we diſown.] <hi>Though there be a truth in it, that how much ſoever a godly man ſinneth, he ſhall be pardoned; yet the Scripture uſeth no ſuch language: and the Form of Wholeſom Words teacheth every man rather to ſpeak thus, If I be wicked, then woe unto me.</hi> Thus far Mr. <hi>Caryl,</hi> to whom I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41495:47"/>And as ſmoothly as Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> thinks to carry it, he forgets, or underſtands not, that Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Elect,</hi> but the other Divines of Believers, which are not <hi>convertible terms;</hi> for though all <hi>Believers</hi> are <hi>Elect,</hi> yet the <hi>Elect</hi> are not <hi>ipſo facto Believers</hi> as ſoon as they exiſt in the World. Now we who hold, that <hi>the Elect are Children of Wrath</hi> as well as others, during their ſtate of unbelief, do yet hold alſo, that to thoſe Elect, being once Believers, there is no condemnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
            <p>As for the denial of <hi>Conditions in the New Covenant</hi> by the other Divines abovementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, I will not conteſt about Terms, if they will but grant, That <hi>the New Covenant is not abſolute, in oppoſition to any Means or Order which God hath appointed for obtaining the Benefits of it;</hi> though I ſee no harm in the term <hi>Condition,</hi> as applied to the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. As for Mr. <hi>Jer. Burroughs</hi> aſſerting of <hi>remiſſion of all ſins, paſt, preſent, and to come;</hi> I ſuppoſe he means with <hi>Ames, that ſins paſt are remitted formally; future ſins but vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. Med. Theol. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. <hi>n.</hi> 24. Becauſe he that hath been forgiven one ſin, ſhall not be condemned for another. See <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13. I find not any thing elſe worth the taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, but his Anſwers to two of our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments againſt their Doctrine of Saints
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41495:47"/>Apoſtacy. 1. <hi>That it is deſtructive of Chriſtian Comfort.</hi> To which he anſwers out of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> That a comfortable life may be led without Aſſurance. To which I reply, That the experience of <hi>Adams</hi> frailty gives us, who have remains of ſin in us, more cauſe to fear our ſtanding, if left (as he) to our ſelves. And 'tis the ſtrongeſt conſolation we are capable of, or can deſire in this life, that <hi>we ſhall be preſerved from every evil work to Gods heavenly Kingdom,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.17. The ſecond Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> pretends to anſwer, is, That <hi>the Saints Apoſtacy makes Gods love changeable.</hi> To which he anſwers, That Gods love is upon condition. I reply, <hi>Gods love</hi> is taken in Scripture two ways, which the Schools call <hi>Amor ordinativus &amp; collativus,</hi> that is, for <hi>Gods purpoſe</hi> of doing men good, which is one and the ſame whilſt Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or Believers; and of this <hi>Love</hi> there nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is nor can be any Condition (as under the ſixth <hi>Argument of Election</hi> I have proved.) And for the <hi>performance of this purpoſe,</hi> or actual collation of the benefits purpoſed; and thus Faith is a qualification of the Subject, neceſſary by the tenor of the Goſpel, to the participation of the benefits tender'd therein. And 'tis <hi>Gods Love</hi> in the former ſenſe, which we ſay were changeable; ſhould he damn any
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41495:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>true Believer. As for his ſtory out of <hi>Dr. Pierce, That woman that believed not that Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery had done her any hurt, nor was damnable in her, nor leſſen'd the favour of God, underſtood not</hi> our Doctrine, for the ſtain of Sin ſurely is an hurt; and the ſtate of Grace takes not away the demerit of Damnation, though it prevents that event; and though the ſins of Believers leſſen not the <hi>favour or love of God,</hi> in the firſt acception above-mentioned, <hi>i. e. makes not his purpoſe of no effect:</hi> Yet it does in the ſecond acception, for it procures God's with-draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. To conclude, I heartily wiſh and pray, That God would remove from Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> the way of Lying, and cloath him with Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and give him Repentance, to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging of the Truth, that he may not be more aſhamed to have his Ignorance known, then deſirous to have it cur'd.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>VVHat Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> relates at the cloſe, of the orderly behaviour of his own Party, and diſorderly of ours, is ſo evidently falſe, That if he had not a Brow of Braſs, he would not have dar'd to charge the innocent, and diſcharge the guilty. I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all indifferent Auditors, whether Mr. <hi>Ives</hi>'s Party's carriage at our Conference, did not confirm the common opinion of ſober Perſons, <hi>viz. That there is not a ruder ſort of People</hi> (<hi>the</hi> Quakers <hi>not excepted</hi>) <hi>than</hi> Arminian Anabaptiſts.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>ERRATA.</hi> Pag. 3. l. 10. for <hi>Affidavit</hi> read <hi>Affirmative.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41495:48"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
